Failure is the aftermath of doubt

Day 00331: Monday, 2016 February 01

I went through my weblog and corrected the malformed IRC URIs. I saw a network mentioned that used to allow Tor users to join, but that now maliciously discriminates against Tor users, thanks in part to wowaname's influence. I briefly considered removing the hyperlink instead of correcting it, but decided not to. There is a difference between censoring the past and simply correcting malformed URIs.

I did not get out of the house as quickly as I wanted to today, but I still made it to the clinic quite early. After waiting in the lobby, a woman called me in to help me with my state-sponsored health insurance application. However, she asked for very little information from me. I brought a copy of the form that I had submitted by postal mail, but it turned out that I did not need it or even any information from it. She printed out the application, then copied it and gave me the copy. Looking through it, it is identical to the one that I submitted via post, but she left most of the fields blank. Honestly, I think that the copy that I submitted is more likely to be approved, as it actually has information on it! The form asks for both a telephone number and an email address, but she only asked for a telephone number, so when I explained that I do not have telephone service, she left them with no way to contact me aside from physical postal mail. Really? A few good things did come of it though. As she presumably kept the original she printed out, as she said that she sent the form in electronically and did not give me the original, someone has proof that I tried to apply, assuming something goes wrong. Next, she gave me proof of submission, which again, could come in handy. Lastly, she explained that coverage, once approved, is back dated to the date that the application was submitted. As long as I had that proof, some (though not all) health service providers will wait for payment until coverage is granted. It is still a gamble to try to use it before you are approved, as they may decline your application and leave you footing the bill, but in an emergency, it could help.

Net, I headed over to the local community college. Along the way, I saw someone else that was sporting a black ring on his right middle finger like I am, but I have no idea if he is actually asexual or not, or if he even knows that it is an asexual symbol.

Once at the school, I made an appointment to see someone about my transfered-in credits. The soonest available appointment in on the tenth, so that is the appointment that I took.

Yesterday, my mother complained that she had forgotten to get groceries, so I offered to pick them up today while I was in the area. She said that it was a long way to carry them on foot, by which she no doubt meant to tell me not to do it, but I did it anyway today. First of all, she did not directly tell me not to. But more importantly, I do not need her making bogus claims that if only I had a car and a driver license, I could have picked up the groceries for her. Both she and I know that if I had a car and a driver license, she would be more willing to send me on errands, but that I would still perform those errands on foot if at all feasible. This was plenty feasible.

One of the local radio stations, the one that my mother listens to, calls itself "K-DOCK". They spell it this way too at their headquarters. This has been quite enigmatic to me, as those are not valid call letters. I had thought that radio stations in the United States used four-letter call signs, though research today indicates that this is false. This station has also caused confusion for my mother, though she did not seem to know it. She kept calling the station "K-DUCK", likely because of the "KDUK" station in Springfield. The radio would announce that "K-DOCK", not "KDUK", had radio station stickers that she wanted, but she said that every time that she went there, they were closed for the day, as she has to work during their business hours. With that in mind, she asked me to drop by "KDUK" if I was ever in the area while they were open and pick one up. I knew that the stickers were at K-DOCK, but figured that I had better do as asked and drop by "KDUK" to pick up one of their stickers if they had one, as that is what I had been asked to do. If I was wrong, and she really did want what she had asked for, she would chew me out later if I had grabbed the wrong ones, but if I was right but grabbed the ones that she had asked for, then she could not really blame me. Likewise, she had convinced me that KDUK is both in Springfield and here in Coos Bay. I do not listen to the radio, as it seems to play only proprietary music, so I took her at her word, not even questioning it until yesterday. I explained that while i know where a couple of the local radio stations are, I have not seen KDUK's building. Yesterday, she showed me where "KDUK" is. It was not KDUK though, but K-DOCK, which I made sure to tell her. In any case, I picked up two of the stickers on the way home. Looking at the stickers, I saw "K-DOCK" in large print, but in small print, I saw the stations actual call letters: KDCQ. "DOCK" is simply an easier-to-recognize spelling of the attempted pronunciation of the letters "DCQ".

Having completed my errands, I headed home. Along the way, with my mobile on shuffle mode, I heard the song Revolution Now by Josh Woodward. It once again reminded me that failure is the aftermath of doubt. That snapped me out of my lingering funk from yesterday. I need to remain strong and not doubt myself, and there is strength in knowledge, which is best gained through information flow. I need to keep my continued contact with friends under wraps, and must refrain from spending too much time socializing as I have other things that need to be done, but if I allow her to convince me to forsake my friendships, she has succeeded in stripping me of my strength and potentially my strength of will. I have rejoined IRC, though my canary will remain dark.

Also along the way home, I thought about the future of my array of default ports relating to different URI schemes. On a later date, I may want to expand it to hold more scheme information that just default port numbers. However, if I complete this constant and have not accounted for the possibility of new features, any code that relies on this constant will break when the array is changed to become multi-dimensional. I must make it multi-dimensional before doing any further work on it. Likewise, in such an update, the constant name will either no longer be quite appropriate, or the constant name will need to be changed, causing breaks in code that relies on it. I need to change the name now, before it is complete. I already have a few things that I want to add to the array at some point: a list of URI components that are valid for use in URIs of the given scheme, the name of a function that can perform any special scheme-specific normalizations, and a boolean that specifies whether URIs of the given scheme can be expected to conform to standard URI syntax, as I have already come across one scheme in which no URI conforms and another in which unnormalized URIs are allowed not to conform. I will likely finish with default port number research before even starting research on the other three specifications. On second thought, I should go back and re-read the specifications and fill out the missing data. That way, I would not have to go back and re-find information that I already found once, at least with the schemes that I have not yet worked with at all yet.

I started at the beginning of the scheme list again, taking a look at RFC 6733, which defines the aaa: and aaas: schemes. Looking more closely than I apparently did last time, I found that in section 4.3.1, the document is self-contradictory. It claims that URIs that use this scheme must conform to the URI syntax set forth in RFC 3986, but also defines the path as being composed of up to two segments that each begin with a semicolon. The host component, and therefor the authority component, is always present and must be a fully-qualified domain name. The path can only contain certain values, and cannot contain a slash. RFC 3986 specifies that if an authority component is present, the path must be empty or begin with a slash, yet RFC 6733 claims to conform to it. I will need to do more than search for an "it conforms" statement in the future.

I have come to the conclusion that I cannot properly test the values in my scheme information array without having both the function that uses these values and the functions mentioned in the values. I will put down the array for a while so I can build my main normalization function, then build the scheme-specific normalization functions as I go.

My mother keeps insisting that it is impossible for a vegetarian diet, and especially a vegan diet, to be healthful. She is failing to comprehend the fact that I am willing to sacrifice my health for this. I am not doing this for improved health. However, it seems that i need to shoot down her argument. Of course, she does not want to do this research herself, even though she is convinced that her position is correct. So today, I found her some information: It is the position of the American Dietetic Association that appropriately planned vegetarian diets, including total vegetarian or vegan diets, are healthful, nutritionally adequate, and may provide health benefits in the prevention and treatment of certain diseases. Well-planned vegetarian diets are appropriate for individuals during all stages of the lifecycle, including pregnancy, lactation, infancy, childhood, and adolescence, and for athletes.. Yes, it is true that I do not strive for nutrition. It is also true that my diet is likely unhealthy, though so is hers. However, my lack of a balanced diet has nothing to do with my veganism.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.1 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Taxes should be fileable electronically directly through the IRS website, but they are not

Day 00332: Tuesday, 2016 February 02

While working on my code that validates the syntax of a $[URI], I ran into an issue. My regular expression for parsing a URI assumes that hosts do not contain colons. However, a host is allowed to be an IPv6 address as long as it is enclosed in brackets. I thought that I was not going to be able to figure out how to fix the expression and I was going to have to split it into two expressions. The first would have parsed most of the information out of the URI but leave the host and port components tangled. The second would have separated the host and port from one another. If I could guarantee that my expression would only be used on URIs that conform to the valid syntax, I could easily parse using only one expression, but because invalid URIs may be passed in, I have to be able to account for them. Though by default, URIs parsed will be run through a syntax validator after being run through the regular expression, the validator needs to be able to tell for sure which part of a malformed URI is the malformed part. Likewise, if the validation is intentionally disabled, the parsing function needs to output the closest approximation of a correct parse. After much struggle, I finally succeeded in writing a single expression that I think will work as best as possible even on malformed URIs.

My task for today was to file my taxes. Unfortunately, the IRS does not allow people to electronically file their taxes through their own website. Instead, taxpayers are required to enlist help from third-party corporations for this. Not having the energy to deal with paper mail forms right now, I chose one of the listed third-party corporations and got started. It was not a fun experience. My first complaint about TurboTax that the site's form began by sniffing my User-Agent string. Any site that does that is poorly-built and likely relies on browser-specific hacks instead of standards-compliant code. It detected that I am using Linux, and said that "some visual elements may not render perfectly". Why does in matter if visual elements render perfectly anyway? If that matters so much, I repeat: use standards-complaint code so that your pages will render as perfectly as possible in every Web browser. The form allowed me to continue though, so I did. The site asked for a telephone number near the beginning, though I left it blank and the form allowed me to continue. It was only *after* I had entered all my information that the site admitted that they were not actually going to allow me to leave that field blank, and it began demanding that i enter a telephone number. This is extremely dishonest and manipulative! My guess is that they want to wait until you reach the end to push because they figure that you will not want to reenter your information on another site, so you will find a way to get ahold of a telephone number to give them if they demand it at the end. They would not even allow me to print my taxes and file via postal mail without handing over a telephone number! They have a support option, but it too requires a telephone number to use, and from the looks of it, you enter your telephone number and then a representative will call you when they can. In other words, you cannot get help with the fact that they do not allow you to move on without telephone service! They have a secondary help option, but it is a community forum. It is unlikely that the people that can actually fix this look over the questions, but I posted there anyway just in case. After a while, I decided to edit the page in-browser to disable the validation of that input field. After several tried, I managed to get it to act as an optional input field so I could move on. The next page of the form asked how I wanted my refund returned to me, but I found that the site tries to discourage the paper check option. Instead, they prefer that you either hand TurboTax your bank account information so that you can get your refund deposited directly into your account, meanwhile TurboTax then has your bank account information for their own records and uses, or take your refund in the form of a prepaid card, in which case TurboTax can charge you fees as you use it, can track your purchases, and can prevent you from depositing the money into an account to make interest. Of course, the paper check option is the safest option, so I chose that. Next, I was asked for state-issued ID, though this was optional, so I skipped it. Once more, the site demanded a telephone number, and due to the site's use of multi-page validation, I was unable to evade the requirement any more. I tried going back and handing over my state-issued ID, but that did not fix the problem. I had to discard my tax submission, and I will submit using another site. I will make note of the fact that TurboTax is underhanded and will not make use of their services ever again. On the plus side, if I give up on using another site, I was able to get a printable copy of my tax return just after having hacked my way past the first telephone number demand page. I do not recommend TurboTax at all.

Next, I tried using Jackson Hewitt's tax preparation service. First, these idiots claimed that they needed to confirm my identity by sending me a verification email. Believe me, I love verification emails, as they prevent people from using my email address to sign up for services and leave me with all the emails from the services. However, at this point in the registration process, they had not even so much as asked for my name, not to mention that email address verification only verifies that you have access to a given email account. This verification *does not* verify your identity. I am glad that unlike TurboTax, they verified my email address, but they need to call it what it is: email address verification, not identity verification. I was just going to let that slide though. A little later in the form, they asked me to give my consent for them to process my information for tax filing purposes by typing my full legal name. So I typed my first and last legal name, which I consider to be my full legal name even though it is not my real name, but they did not accept that. Next, I tried my first, middle, and last legal names, but they did not accept that either. It turned out that what they wanted was my first legal name, my middle legal initial, and my last legal name. That is not my full legal name in any sense of that phrase! If an initial is used at all, it is not a full name. I was aggravated by this, but I of course continued. Next, I hit the wall in their service. They too require a telephone number, though at least they admit it up front. They do not allow you to leave it blank so that you enter all the rest of your information, then demand the telephone number later. While Jackson Hewitt's tax preparation service seems to contain idiocies, at least they do not appear to contain dishonesty. They are upfront about what they demand. I was going to leave and look for another tax e-filing service, but I noticed a "live chat" option as I was starting to log out. Their live chat support people were offline by the time I was using their site, but the times that they are online were listed. I will speak with them tomorrow and see if anything can be done. As a last resort, as I said earlier, I have a printable copy of the filled forms, so I can mail them in if every service listed on the IRS website demands a telephone number.

I received an email from the Albanian mafia, offering their services as hitmen. First, they explained about Tor a little, then onion space and how to reach it. The short Tor lesson was amusing, though I do not like the negative light that they shine on onion space. Of course, there is the issue of them killing people, which is not something that I condone, but also, they say that it is used by criminals (not only themselves, either) to evade the law. To someone that does not already know about onion space, it makes it sound like onion space is simply a place for criminals. There is more here than that though. There are illegal things here, that is true, but there are also semi-private things such as the site of someone I know that prefers not to be mentioned, silly things such as Anonymous Cat Facts, freedom of information sites such as Liberated Books and Papers, anti-DRM sites such as the Radical Militant Library (which is not really all that militant as far as I can tell), public tools such as Anon PasteBin, and sites that just want to be slightly detached from the legal identity of the webmaster and run from behind the walls put up by a restrictive ISP, such as my own site here. There is more here in onion space than just murder and illegal drugs.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Filing taxes

Day 00333: Wednesday, 2016 February 03

I found a couple interesting facts about URIs today. First, IPv6 addresses uses as hosts in URIs are not normalized. There are several valid ways to write an IPv6 address, depending on which zeros you want to omit. You could leave out all the zeros that you can, you could explicitly include every zero, or anything in between. However, URIs that differ only in which zeros are omitted are not defined as being equivalent. The second thing that I learned has to do with IPv4 addresses that are written in their single-decimal form. Tor does not handles these IP addresses correctly, or so I thought. It turns out that this IP address format is not valid in URIs, and should not work when using any URI resolver. Systems tend not to be as strict as they should be when resolving URIs though, and sometimes bad URIs will be resolved in platform-dependent ways.

I spoke with Jackson Hewitt's tech support about the telephone number issue, explaining that the tax preparation form was not allowing me to leave this field blank and that I have no telephone service. First, they tried to justify it, saying that the telephone number is needed in case the IRS needs to contact me. I assume the implication was that Jackson Hewitt does not use this number and that I would be okay with the IRS calling me, which makes no sense seeing as I said that I have no telephone service, not that I did not want to give out my existing number. After explaining that again, the support representative said that she would check for a way to bypass the requirement, and came back with the answer of using the telephone number 800 555 1212. I assume based on the format that that is intended to be a dead number, but it is not. Dead numbers are in the "XXX 555 01XX" ranges excluding the "800 555 01XX" range, in which only one of those numbers (800 555 0199) is actually dead. In any case, I now have explicit permission to use this number for this tax preparation service, so if I need to come back here, I can move on. However, I would rather not use any telephone number, be it one that leads to me or not. I do not like the telephone number system and do not want to be associated with a telephone number. I did some research, and it turns out that 800 555 1212 is the number to call to reach directory assistance for telephone numbers within the 800 area code.

The next service that I tried was H&R block. When I got to the telephone number field, it had the description text The IRS requires a valid daytime phone number., but still allowed me to leave it blank. Later on in the process though, their system did go back and require this information, information that I do not even have. I suppose that their system is more honest than TurboTax's system, as TurboTax's system silently allows you to continue without a telephone number, then after you enter all your information, they demand the telephone number. Still, if they are going to require this, they should not allow you to continue without filling the field, as that just causes frustration after you have entered all your tax information. That sentence though, The IRS requires a valid daytime phone number., makes me think that maybe it does not matter which tax preparation service I use. Perhaps they are only conforming to some idiotic requirement imposed by the IRS.

Next, I tried eSmart. They asked for both a telephone number and email address, asking which I preferred to be contacted by. I thought that this was finally my chance to avoid specifying a telephone number! However, though they allowed me to leave that field blank at first, they did go back after I had entered all my information and demand a telephone number. I contacted live support, who said that I had to enter a telephone number to move on. Once more, I explained that I do not have telephone service and asked if that meant that I needed to find a different tax preparation service. She said that that was something that I needed to decide, as if I could choose to use this service without a telephone number. I clarified the situation, laying out the two options: using the service without a telephone number or using a different service. I explained that if I really do get to choose, I would prefer to use the service, then, I asked once more if I had to choose a different service. She asked if she could have her supervisor call me, again, seeming to not comprehend the fact that I have no telephone service. I said that that would be fine as long as she did not mean call me on the telephone, again explaining that I do not have telephone service, and she offered to have her supervisor email me instead. People without telephone service still need to file tax returns and there needs to be a way for us to do so.

At this point, I think that I want to try as many of the services as I can in order to let as many of them know as I can that not everyone has telephone service and that the telephone number requirement is ridiculous. That said, I was tired of insecure "security" questions. As such, I do not want to file my state and federal tax returns with two separate services, so I ruled out any option that did not provide an all-in-one service. Likewise, I do not *want* to pay taxes to my country's evil government, I just have to, so I refuse to pay for the privilege of filing taxes that I do not even want to pay, so I ruled out any services that cost money. Besides, I am short on funds and every saved dime helps right now. I found one service that will be gratis on February 15, but I would like to have my taxes filed by then, so I ruled it out as well.

Lastly, I tried filing my taxes through TaxAct. Their telephone number field had the explanation text Providing the IRS with your daytime phone number may help speed the processing of your return., which implied that the telephone number was not necessary if speed was not necessary. Likewise, TaxAct accepted my legal first and last name as my signature. Later on in the process, they pestered me again for a telephone number, but once more, they allowed me to leave it blank and they submitted my tax forms on my behalf without it. In future years, if I want to avoid issues, I should remember to try TaxAct first.

I received an answer on the TurboTax forum about my issues with their service and being unable to move on without entering a telephone number that I do not have. However, the person that answered the question just told me that I should enter a messaging number if I do not have a telephone number. That makes no sense, assuming that by a "messaging number" they actually mean an SMS-enabled telephone number, as that is still a telephone number, which I made clear that I do not have.

I forgot to comment on something that i saw at my mother's school the other day. Someone there was helping her set up dynamic message templates that would add specific sentences to her students' grade reports to explain how they were doing. These templates would automatically change the pronoun to either "he" or "she", depending on the sex of the child. I remember thinking that this sort of hacky workaround would not be needed if our language did not foolishly include sex/gender-based pronouns. There is no good reason for them.

I have never looked into what generation I am a member of because I simply do not care. It is just a label, after all. However, my brother informed me that I am a member of Generation Y. That is awesome! Out of all the letters I could have ended up with as my second-level domain, I ended up with wye, and I also am a member of Generation Y. The coincidence is of course meaningless, but I still find it to be a fun fact.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Sinking in the sand

Day 00334: Thursday, 2016 February 04

I found a new Web browser theme for Firefox that I like, so I installed it in Iceweasel. It combines three things that i love: Debian, dark themes, and code.

I finished the main functions of my new URI-handling code. By ignoring the scheme-specific stuff for now, I was able to get my spider back up and operational. Basically, the only thing keeping the spider inactive for so long was my merge_uris() function, which depended on PHP's broken \parse_url() function. With my own parse_uri() function built and merge_uris() fixed, the spider only needed some light patching to use the new functions. I also updated the spider to remove all calls to \parse_url() before running it. I considered putting off work on the spider until my URI-handling code is completely finished, but the spider will take quite a while to run. If I get it started, I can work on the scheme-specific code while I wait for errors to inevitably reveal themselves during spider code execution. Currently, my function that calls the scheme-specific functions will not do so unless a specific constant array with necessary information has been defined, so it basically does not need the scheme-specific code, but has a hook through which I can cause it to execute that code once it is finished. I will wait until tomorrow to upload my work on include.d and the spider, giving the spider a bit more time to run into bugs that need to be fixed in both itself and especially in include.d.

I meant to work on the FAFSA after finishing the main functions of my new URI-handling code today, but I did not get around to that. Instead, I ended up traveling to the local beach with my family. Vanessa wanted to go, but opted not to once our mother got home, as our mother does not like the local beach and Vanessa did not want to exclude her. However, oddly enough, our mother wanted to go too, so we did go after all. I had traveled all the way from the beach access point to the far end of the walkable beach in one direction before, but we ended up traveling in the opposite direction. I do not know if it was because we were on a different section of the beach or because the sand was unusually wet today, but the ground kept sinking on us. The ground was full of holes and water, and as we stepped, we would sink into the sand, making it difficult to walk. Due to my mother being strange about me carrying a bag, I did not bring it, which was sort of a mixture of good and bad. I needlessly became dehydrated, but the bag is also heavy and would have caused me to sink deeper into the sand. Vanessa, Cyrus, and our mother started catching crabs to feed to the fish in our mother's school's aquarium, though I do not think that Vanessa and Cyrus were happy about their fate.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

The spider seems to be running smoothly now

Day 00335: Friday, 2016 February 05

My task for today was to complete my FAFSA. It went very smoothly. Of note, it was possible to leave the telephone number blank, despite that message I received that claimed that government forms usually require a telephone number even from people that do not have one.

I ran into a bug before I went to bed last night in which the spider assumes that every normalized URI has a host component, which was then triggered by the presence of a URI using the javascript: scheme. I did not remember seeing that one on the official scheme list, so I took another look. It is not listed! There are a bunch of schemes listed there that almost no one uses, yet the fairly-well-known javascript: scheme did not make the cut. In any case, I have repaired that bug in the spider. When I woke up, I found that a bug that I had intentionally coded into the spider had been set off as well. Namely, I programed it to assume that all URIs that it finds are valid. My functions are designed to throw exceptions in case of malformed URIs, but the spider was not designed to catch them. I knew that this bug would cause an issue eventually, I just did not realize that it would be so soon. Some people just do not know how to form a valid URI, which I think is the case here, but also you should never trust user input. I hate to blindly ignore these bad URIs, but I do not know what else to do. For now, the spider now tries to make sense of each URI, but it the syntax is invalid, it catches the exception, outputs an error message that will not be seen as it will be buried in all the other output, then moves on to the next URI. I suppose that I will need to start greping the log from now on.

I wrote a couple of the new scheme-specific normalization functions, but then I decided to delete them and remove the callback hook from the main normalization function. This is starting to lead off on an unnecessary tangent. If someone wants to compare two URIs for equivalence, they should probably use both the generic URI normalization function and, if necessary, a scheme-specific URI normalization function. I also removed the parts of the function that normalize the port component based on the default port of a given scheme and checks for the presence of URI components that are required or forbidden by a given scheme as well. I considered leaving them, as at least the port normalization is useful to me, but they seem like they are outside the scope of the function. I need a function that can take the place of PHP's broken \parse_url() function. The RFC 3986-specified normalization goes a bit beyond that, though it is quite useful when trying to keep a list of pages and sites that the spider has already visited and is generic enough to be useful in many cases. Anything scheme-specific is outside the scope of that function though and should be delegated to another function if that functionality is required.

I received an email from eSmart reminding me to finish filing my taxes through them even though they have not had one of the supervisors get back to me. Because of their letter, I pestered them on Twitter a bit, as they included a link to their Twitter account in their email. On Twitter, they gave me the support email address! I doubt that I will pursue this, but if I wanted to, I have another method.

It seems that my mother is going to Portland for some training and she will be dropping me off in Springfield along the way. There, I will work on cleaning up our former residence through Thursday, Friday, and Saturday. I may not have Internet access during that time though, so I may not update this weblog until I get back.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.1 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

The spider does not handle broken markup well

Day 00336: Saturday, 2016 February 06

I feel like I am stuck waiting for the time being. Until my appointment on Wednesday, in which I will learn what courses I would need to take to pursue finishing my associate degree at the local community college, I will not know whether I will be going back to school or attempting to find a full-time job for the time being. I cannot really make any plans until then.

While the spider continues to run without error, I do not have any fatal bugs to work on, so it is time to work on feature support. The main two features on the waiting list are support for retrieving the full text of an <a/> tag even when it has child nodes and support for flat file databases. I think that it would be a lot of fun to try abstracting away the direct database calls, which would make supporting flat files and multiple database software options as easy as writing a new class, one that implements a particular interface, for each storage method desired. However, the <a/> tag issue is of more urgency, even if of less importance, so I set to work on that instead.

Setting up that functionality turned out to be quite trivial. I set up a mock function that, if built, should provide exactly what I need to easily extract link text regardless of nesting. However, before I could build it, I ran some tests on some broken XML to see how PHP's XML parser deals with broken XML. As it turns out, it does not. As soon as an error is encountered, parsing stops. This is the proper behavior, but I had thought that I had tested the XML parser on HTML (which is basically malformed XML before. I had looked for some sort of error though, so when reasonable-looking data was returned, I must have assumed that it had not given up on the document. Partial data like this is probably worse than no data, as with partial data, I think that I have everything on the page parsed and do not realize that there is a bug in need of fixing.

To be fair though, use of HTML and other broken markup is the real bug. But though the bug is not on my end, I need to be able to deal with it on my end.

I added output to estimate the time remaining in the processing of a website, as it can be a bit bothersome waiting for the spider to be finished with a large website so that I can halt and restart it to see an update take effect. Next, I worked on improving my URI handlers. In reality, a URI is a specialized kind of data, so it would be better implemented as a class than as several functions like it was yesterday when I finished it. Additionally, as a class, it will only need to check the URI components for validity during parsing, instead of both during parsing and during reconstruction. I think that I have the class working correctly, but I did not have time to test it tonight, so I will wait until tomorrow to upload it and integrate it with the spider.

While combining the URI-related functions into a class, I came across a corner case that I had not accounted for. URIs such as example:/.// seem to be valid, though unnormalized. Using the standard normalization method though, the path becomes ///. With no host component present, the path cannot begin with two slashes. However, normalizing the path is not allowed to alter the host component, so we cannot normalize the URI to example:/// and say that the new path is /. I have no idea how to properly normalize this URI. For the time being, I set up a loop that is entered when this type of situation is encountered. As long as the first two characters of the path are both slashes, one will be removed and the loop will continue. I am not sure that this is the correct way to handle this situation, but it is a better idea than any of the alternatives I came up with, such as encoding one of the slashes as %25 or prefixing the path with some character do that the path did not start with a slash at all.

I spent most of the day running errands in Springfield with my mother. It seems that my presence was not really needed though and I was not able to help.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Importing functions and constants

Day 00337: Sunday, 2016 February 07

I reworked my Gopher index handler to spit out objects of the URI class instead of strings. In addition to making the output more usable, this also breaks the Gopher index handler's dependence on \parse_url(), which it had been using as a light-wight validation method (it did not insure that the URI was completely valid, but it insured that it was valid enough to be handled by other functions that relied on \parse_url()). I then finished work modifying the spider to use my new uri class instead of the the old functions that I merged to create it. I thought that it might not work out of the box, as I was unsure if \in_array() performed strict or loose comparisons, but it looks like it thankfully can do both. It defaults to loose comparisons, which is exactly what I need for comparing two uri objects for equivalence.

To deal with broken markup that the spider encounters, I though that I was going to have to build my own parser. However, it seems that PHP has me covered. \DOMDocument::loadHTML() can deal with broken markup. Also of use will be \DOMDocument::getElementsByTagName(), which will make it easy to find all the <a/>, <base/>, and <loc/> tags. For my website compilation scripts, \DOMDocument::validate() will be very nice, as I can validate my pages as they are generated instead of needing to validate them by hand later.

I started work on the updating the spider to use the \DOMDocument class instead of the wrapper\xml class but starting to convert the base URI handler, but it looks like the \DOMDocument class takes care of finding the base URI and passes this information on to the \DOMElement class. Finding the base URI once at the beginning of the page seems like the most efficient way to handle the issue of <base/> tags, but making use of this feature in the \DOMDocument and \DOMElement classes seems like it might be the more correct option, as it insures that my code is not handling the <base/> tags directly, so there is less chance of bugs in my code. Until I see a way to set different bases for different elements of an XHTML/HTML page, I think that I will use the more efficient option of finding the base once myself instead of constantly instantiating new uri objects for each <a/> tag. After finishing the conversion, I ran into an issue. \DOMDocument::loadHTML() throws error when it finds malformed markup, even when I set the options that supposedly disable it! I asked for advice on the issue, but I had to leave quickly.

While we were out today, my mother tried to backpedal on something that she had said to me before. She now claims that her issue with me carrying a drink only applies when I am alone, not when I am with her. I have several issues with this. First of all, this is dishonest. Before, she specifically mentioned a situation that she did not want me having a drink in which I am only in when I am with her: working in her classroom. Second, when I am out on my own is when I need a drink the most. I am not giving up being hydrated when she is not even around to care.

Cyrus, our mother, and I went out to the hills to gather bullet shells, which she is collecting to sell for the copper, but also finds collecting them to be fun. At first, I was very anxious to get back home. My spider was down. When the spider is running, I can at least figure that it is making progress without me, but as long as that error was keeping the spider out of commission, no progress was being made unless I was making progress myself in fixing the error. However, I came to the conclusion that perhaps what I was doing in the hills was more important. The money made will likely not even cover the gasoline costs of the drive out there. However, it was time spent doing something that she wanted to do. She needs something pleasant in her life, seeing as her job is so taxing.

When we got back home, I found two responses to my question. The first was unhelpful, saying that the only software that I would be able to find that repairs malformed markup like I need it to would be a Web browser. This person did not understand the issue. The \DOMDocument class was *already* repairing the document. The issue was that it was also spewing minor errors as it did so. The second person's response was much more practical and useful. They said to set \DOMDocument::$recover to true and call \libxml_use_internal_errors() with a boolean true before attempting to parse the document, then call \libxml_clear_errors() after. \DOMDocument::$recover did not need to be changed to fix the problem. The other two did the trick! However, by setting \DOMDocument::$recover to true anyway, I was able use \DOMDocument::loadXML() instead of \DOMDocument::loadHTML(), which prevented some errors generated during the parsing of perfectly well-formed sitemaps, as \DOMDocument::loadHTML() was complaining about elements that are not present in HTML.

I have been a bit frustrated because I have not been able to import functions and constants into the current name space. It is not the missing feature that has been bothering me either, it is the fact that it has not worked on my copy of PHP, but the feature supposedly was added in a version slightly older than mine. So if the feature was made available prior to my version, where is it? Well, it turns out that I need to pay more attention when reading the manual. I assumed that the syntax for importing functions and constants was the same as that for importing classes and namespaces; the reason for this assumption being that the syntax for importing a name space is identical to the syntax for importing a class. In fact, if a class and a namespace shared a name, I think that it would be impossible to import one without importing the other at the same time. However, it seems that for functions and constants, it is a little different. Tomorrow, I will go through and clean up the spider code to use proper imports. While I am at it, I should clean up the settings file and the code that pulls values from it.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

I wish that the SQL standard was actually adhered to

Day 00338: Monday, 2016 February 08

After cleaning up the configuration and use of name spaces in the spider, I started work on abstracting the database interactions. That way, it would be possible to build a class for each type of database and use whichever class was needed for a given type of database. As classes, new database types could be added easily and database-specific logic would not need to be messily strewn about throughout the spider's main logic. I started by trying to build a class to abstract away the \mysqli class' methods, keeping a copy of an actual \mysqli class instance as a property of my class. I quickly realized that this was the wrong way to build my class though. My class should extend the \mysqli class, allowing instances to to have the full range of functionality available to both \mysqli objects and object of classes implementing my database interface.

While working on the MySQL implementation of my database interface, I quickly ran into an issue that I had not before: MySQL does not have support for boolean data. A database should reasonably be able to store a boolean value, so I had added that to the interface, but now it was being problematic. It seems that MySQL does not have basic boolean support! I could implement the feature using a single-digit unsigned integer, a string, or even as a single bit itself, but that does not fix the issue. When retrieving the data later, how can I tell the difference between a boolean and data that is actually meant to be whatever type of data I have implemented the boolean as? I could implement all data types as strings, use the first character as a flag to tell what type of data is being used, and perform my own processing, but that would remove much of the database-specific optimization that MySQL (and later database applications that I work with) probably has. I could rely on the script making use of the abstraction classes to know that certain data types are not properly implemented and perform needed conversions, but that removes part of the abstraction, as which types function correctly is database-specific. I could also implement only strings, so the calling script would know that everything going into or coming out of the database is a string, but that too would remove helpful database-specific internals optimizations. Another option would be to rely on the calling script to know what type it was expecting and call appropriate methods such as database::get_bool(), but that would only allow looking data up one grid square at a time. Full and partial rows would require performing several lookups, which would cause a serious performance drop. I though that this would be a simple subproject, but it might turn into a full-blown project of its own.

I have heard that PHP's \PDO class does not provide abstraction; it only provides a consistent interface. I also hear that most SQL database software applications do not correctly implement standard SQL. Perhaps using some subset of features, I can use standard SQL statements in combination with the \PDO class and actually make progress. The catch is, of course, that even if this works, it would only allow use of multiple types of database software back ends to be used; it would not allow a way to use a flat file database structure if desired. I think that I will switch to \PDO tomorrow for the time being. If I come up with a better option, I would be happy to switch, but I should not wait around for an idea in the mean time. If anyone reports problems in compatibility, I can set up some arrays of database-specific SQL queries that can be referenced as needed. Even better, I could set up separate files for each database application containing only the queries needed by each specific database application, and one can be require()d based on some configuration value.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Making better use of exceptions and an attempt at database freedom

Day 00339: Tuesday, 2016 February 09

Today, I thought that it would be a good idea to clean up my use of exceptions. Until today, I have been throwing exceptions of predefined types without giving my exceptions any distinguishing features. Sure, I set the error messages of the exceptions, but those are not very useful when determining if you have caught the expected exception. There are a few ways that I could make my exceptions stand out. The easiest would be to define my own exception classes for each situation in which I need to throw an exception. This seems like overkill though, as least for my current use case. The second option is to set an error code and use the exception's getCode() method to retrieve it and compare it against a known value. The problem with this option is that the default exceptions only accept integer error codes. If I could use a string, I could set the code to the name of the throwing class/function, so I could distinguish between exceptions thrown by the class/function that I am expecting an exception from and exceptions thrown because of unexpected errors. Again, I could define my own exception classes in order to add the option of using string error codes, but I would either be giving up the option of using a fitting exception class for each case or I would need to define several essentially-identical exceptions, each of which extend a different predefined exception class. My next option would be to choose a large integer that people are not likely to choose and use that as the exception code. This has the advantage that the standard exception classes could still be used, but the disadvantage that the integers are not easily memorable or easily recognizable. They could be easily tested against if thrown from within a class though, as the class could have a constant self::EXCEPTION_CODE, which would be visible and comparable within catch() blocks. This would not be helpful for exceptions thrown from functions, but would work for my use case. I throw exceptions from functions only when I want the calling script to die. In classes though, throwing exceptions is useful for preventing instantiation, in which case the script may still need to continue. My final option would be to set an unused property of the exception to the string value that I desire. That has the advantage of not needing any new exceptions defined and still having recognizable values, but relies on people using include.d to recognize the fact that although the exceptions I throw are of the standard type, but that they are somehow different and may need to be treated different. That just sounds like messy coding.

I decided to define the self::EXCEPTION_CODE constant and use integer exception codes based on the hash of the class' name. To fit within the bounds of the integer value type, it does need to be truncated and wrapped from unsigned signed. It seems that if a float is used during class instantiation, no error will be raised, but the float will be ignored and the default error code of zero will be used. To provide better cross-platform support, I will keep my error codes within the 32-bit integer range. Once I had the self::EXCEPTION_CODE constant implemented, I found an exception method that made a lot more sense to use: \Exception::getFile(). This method returns the name of the file in which the exception was thrown, which is a much more logical way to determine if the error came from a particular one of my classes or functions, seeing as each class and function is in its own file. Classes can implement a constant that is set using the __FILE__ keyword for ease, but determining the origin of an exception thrown from a function can be fairly-well identified by running the output of \Exception::getFile() through \substr(). That freed up the error code value to be used for more fine-tuned processing. I am not sure that I have a use for the error codes myself, but I have added a different error code for each line that throws an exception so that these cases can be handled differently if needed.

After setting proper error codes, I thought about using that same hashing technique for setting the values of constants that are meant to be used as options. These values are arbitrary, and I had been setting them according to alphabetical order of the constants used by a given class for options for input into functions. The hashing idea seems like a good option though. After all, these constants are meant to be used as-is; their values are arbitrary and should not be used directly. However, I decided on something better. To express both the arbitrary nature of these values and the fact that they are volatile and subject to change, I can set them using the __LINE__ keyword. It is useful to have the exception codes be unique across classes, but the option codes do not need to be. There is no point in hashing anything meaningful, I just need to take advantage of the arbitrary data that exists simply because that line of code exists. I checked through my classes though, and it appears that I no longer have any such option constants. I must have only used them with wrapper classes so far, so when I deleted most of those, I deleted the constants with them. I will use this approach for any relevant classes in the future.

Having finished my improvements to my exception-based code, I next focused on my intended task for the day: converting the spider to use the \PDO class instead of the \mysqli class. I had planned for a simple method swap for the most part, but the documentation for the \PDO::quote() method insisted that I should instead use \PDO::prepare() to generate prepared statements that would later be run by passing an array of values instead of a query in string form. Reluctantly, I restructured all of my database logic to accommodate. The \PDOStatement::execute() method is less than pleasant to use. It can be used in two ways, one of which seems very messy and requires needless extra legwork and the other of which just requires needless extra leg work. If I understand correctly, the first option requires you to set up variables that are not passed into the method, but act as both input into and output from the method, presumably in some sort of bizarre pass-by-reference move taken to the next level of strangeness. Also, the output retrieved using the more sensible option returns arrays with double the needed number of elements by default. One set of elements is indexed by name, the other by integer. I never could find a way to make the class return arrays using only the named indexes, but there was an option for making the class return instances of another class instead of arrays. These class instances had only named properties, no numbered properties. This option allow any arbitrary class be used for the purpose, or presumably, any arbitrary class that allows simple instantiation and allows public access to the properties that need to be set (which vary based on the query being performed). My main goal was just to get rid of the extra unneeded numeric keys, I did not need any special functionality. With that in mind, I just used the generic \stdClass, which worked perfectly. In any case, hopefully the new code will be compatible with several database options.

While working with the spider code, I found a strange error in how sitemaps were being handled. Instead of adding them to the queue, the spider was setting the current-page URI to that of the sitemap. Before this change could have any effect, the current-page URI was set to that of a page from the queue, so sitemaps were essentially being ignored. I also found a section of the code that had not been updated to use the \DOMDocument class' output, still relying on the output format of my wrapper\xml class. The spider was two days into crawling a website that it said it had four days left to work on, but I decided to kill it prematurely anyway. I will not be here when the spider finishes with that site and I do not want the data format error to kill the spider while I am away, nor do I want the spider to continue ignoring sitemaps. The sitemap fix is probably just a formality though. I am not sure that many people in onion space expect search engine spiders to come crawling, so they likely do not have robots.txt files or sitemaps set up.

While learning how to use the \PDO class and its related classes, I found a new exception class: \PDOException. My understanding of the exception inheritance tree is now as follows:

\Throwable

\Error

\ArithmeticError

\DivisionByZeroError

\AssertionError
\ParseError
\TypeError

\Exception

\ErrorException
\LogicException

\BadFunctionCallException

\BadMethodCallException

\DomainException
\InvalidArgumentException
\LengthException
\OutOfRangeException

\RuntimeException

\OutOfBoundsException
\OverflowException
\PDOException
\RangeException
\UnderflowException
\UnexpectedValueException

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

The \DatePeriod class

Day 00340: Wednesday, 2016 February 10

My project for today was to update my code to use the \DateTime class instead of integer timestamps. While fixing up my day_number class, I quickly found the main problem with using the \DateTime class: it requires instantiation via a date in the form of a string. Because several date formats are accepted, dates that are outside the expected range are not handled correctly. For example, the year 7 is interpreted as being an alias of the year 2007, though this can be overcome by specifying the year as 0007; the year 10000 causes an error with no workaround. I imagine that these corner cases are not the only issue. Once a \DateTime object has been instantiated, the date can be modified using integers, so I extended the class and used this functionality to fix up the constructor method. Once I had a functional base class, I hound that my day_number class, which now extends my fixed datetime class, came together much more smoothly than when it was using timestamps. Due to the fact that telling the timestamp functions to ignore daylight savings time raises an error, I had been having to rely on hacky workarounds instead. Now, everything just fell into place. Next, I worked on fixing my calendar function. It has now been upgraded to being a class and also extends my datetime class. While setting this class up, I found the \DatePeriod class. As a function, calendar() returned a two-dimensional array to be iterated over by a pair of nested foreach() statements. However, the \DatePeriod class, with zero modifications, took all the effort out of building the second dimension, allowing me to remove some somewhat kludgey code. Having the calendar class itself implement the \Iterator interface made the outer iteratable code a bit less concise, but easer to read and understand. Finally, I set to work on fixing up my date_nav() function. After staring at the code a while, I decided to scrap the function altogether. Its main advantage was that it did the leg work of timestamp manipulation for my navigation links. However, making use of the \DateTimeImmutable class and the \DateInterval class, this was a lot less necessary. Implementing this code as a function that made use of the date/time classes would have been messier than just using the date/time classes directly and implementing this code as a class would have been messier still.

I was going to implement a similar feature for a descendant of the \DateTimeImmutable class as I did for a decedent of the \DateTime class, but I decided that it would be too kludgey for now. Due to these objects being immutable, at least in regards to their date and time, I could not use the same simple trick as I had used with the \DateTime class. It could be accomplished using either a non-class function or a static method, but until this functionality is required, I do not want to write such messy code.

I walked over to the local community college today for my appointment with a counselor about the credits that I transfered in. It seems that there was bad news. I had only one course left to complete to get my associate degree at my last school, but I have about a year's worth of courses left to take at this school because so many of the credits did not transfer over like I was told that they would. Even most of the ones that did transfer over did not meet many of the specific requirements and are just being used to fill all of the elective requirements. I do not expect to be in the area beyond the end of next term, so I asked about the school's online options. That lead to even more grim news. Offline, I could earn a degree in a tech field, but online, the only options are general education degrees. I will speak with my mother after I return from Springfield. On the way out, I was offered a chance to get a school ID card, but I was not told that it required a photograph. My hair is still too long, so I would rather avoid getting photo ID right now. Luckily, there were technical difficulties, but even if there were not, it seems that the had left out another important piece of information: students cannot get their student ID cards until *after* enrolling for courses, and I have not done that yet. I only just got the information on what courses I even need today.

Tomorrow, I will be headed to Springfield to work on cleaning up and sorting things at our former residence. I think that I will be returning on Saturday.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

"included"

Day 00341: Thursday, 2016 February 11

Seeing as I did not have much time today, I got my stuff gathered up for heading to Springfield, then looked for a small project I could work on that I could easily walk away from if I did not finish in time. I decided to put together a README file for include.d, explaining what I expect of people that choose to make pull requests against it, assuming that ever happens, and explaining the file-naming conventions that need to be understood in order to make proper use of the code in other projects. NotABug.org is condensing spaces on the main include.d page and mistakingly interpreting the file as Markdown on the file's page, but aside from that, I it came out well.

My mother came home early today. I thought that I had misremembered the time that she was coming by to pick me up! Thankfully, I was mostly ready to go and just had to take care of a couple quick items and I could walk out. However, it seems that she came home sick. For all I knew, I might not be headed to Springfield and she might miss her training in Portland.

While she rested in an attempt to feel better, I did not want to start a major project such as finding a way for my spider to recognize when websites are down. Instead, I started building long-overdue test cases for include.d.

It occurred to me today that if you remove the dot from the name "include.d", you get the real word "included". This was not my intention, but I like it. The actual intention was that it was built to be put in the include path, you could use the include keyword to import the functions and constants (though I personally prefer the require keyword), and Debian sometimes used a ".d" suffix to denote that a file is a directory. I wish that I had been creative enough for the word "included" to be part of why I initially chose the name, but at least now I can retroactively make that a part why I am continuing to use that name.

We did end up going to Springfield, where she dropped me off at he old house, then she continued on to Portland for her training. On the way to Springfield, she asked about what I had found out at the school yesterday, so I told her sooner than I was expecting to. She suggested looking into other local schools and their online offerings. I have also been given two errands to perform tomorrow. First, I need to return a long-overdue school cello to the middle school, then I must make my way to the power and water company to pay a bill and pick up copies of other past bills.

It seems that while the official I2P IRC network has shut down their onion address, wowaname operates an unofficial relay to their network! I think that I will actually bother to set up an account there now when time allows.

As I was away from home, I got to test out reaching cepo via SSH through onion space. It works! I thought that it would, but I had not bothered to test until I actually needed this connection.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Happy Parallel

Day 00342: Friday, 2016 February 12

When I returned the cello and music book today, the person in the school office asked who I was returning it for. I did not want Vivian to get in trouble for having kept it for several years, but I was prepared for such a question. There was a name sticker on the book with my sister's name on the book, but I had already peeled it off revealing the name of the person that had used the book before her. If asked who I was, I would have used my real first name but the former user's last name, resulting in the name "Yst Ryan". I was not asked for my name, but when asked who I was delivering it for, I replied "Alison Ryan", which was believable because it was the name on the book. I got the feeling though that they were asking who to deliver the instrument to, but I was not prepared for that question and answered before realizing what was really being asked. After I left, they might have tried to find out which class Alison Ryan was in or dropped it off at the orchestra room with a note saying that it was the cello of Alison Ryan.

Next, I walked downtown to the utility board to pay the bill and pick up documents. The representative was not expecting me and asked if my mother had called ahead to tell them that I was coming. I told her that she did, so she checked in the back to see what she could find, then came back with a thickly-packed letter-mailing envelope, presumably packed full of folded documents. Between the school and the utility board, it had started to rain, so my mother is lucky that I refuse to stop carrying my bag when she is not around to care. Thanks to the bag, her documents remained dry.

I did not get as much cleaned up at the house as I had hoped to today. Hopefully I can make a lot more progress tomorrow.

While I worked, I listened to music. After listening to several different shuffled sets of tracks, I put Brandt Cooley's Happy Parallel. Typically, I do not hear much of this album. When I put all my music on shuffle, sheer probability keeps me from hearing much from this album. When I put Professor Shyguy's work on shuffle, this album gets left out because most of his work is under the name "Professor Shyguy" while this album is under the name "Brandt Cooley", so the mobile thinks that these are two different artists and does not combine their music. Now that I am actually hearing it, I think that this is perhaps his best album! My understanding is that this album was produced before he took on the name "Professor Shyguy", and from the sound of the album, it was before he started working with chiptune. Come to think of it though, I also really enjoy Unplugged: Please Check Connection, Professor Shyguy's non-chiptune album, so perhaps I like Professor Shyguy's work better when he puts down the chiptune and picks up more traditional instruments. Do not get me wrong though, his chiptune music is awesome too!

I am lucky that the neighbor has an open Wi-Fi connection. Without it, I would not have been able to update my weblog yesterday or today.

Document modifications

On 2018-01-16, my sister, Vivian, requested that I replace all instances of her legal name in my journal with the name "Vivian". She also asked that the name of the organisation she works for be redacted. This page was modified to fulfil that request.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

My mother has her first ex-husband's high school diploma ...

Day 00343: Saturday, 2016 February 13

I think that I realized why I find Happy Parallel so enchanting. I already knew that Brandt is a skilled non-chiptune musician from listening to Unplugged: Please Check Connection, but Happy Parallel has something more. It lacks all the references to proprietary games! I love listening to his songs about proprietary games because the songs themselves are free, but I think that it is easier for me to get into the music when those topics are removed. In fact, of his chiptune works, it is the ones that lack such references that I love most, such as Science, Life, & ABCs, Keywords & Dubstep, My Simple Pop Song, and Ana Ng. I had not really noticed this pattern before.

It seems that OFTC has blacklisted several of wowaname's user names, preventing them from being used, not only by her, but by anyone. They also dropped the name "wowaname" from registration, allowing someone else to register it. Of course, this does not at all prevent her from connecting the way that it would me. If you take away my ability to use my name, I leave. Most people are not like that though, and will simply choose a new name. Furthermore, wowaname is known for ban evasion, so a simple name block is not going to keep her out. By blocking her names, all that they have done is made it harder to identify her when she does connect. She annoyed them with her trolling, but their attempts to keep her off the network are shoddy at best and are completely counterproductive.

I quit using embelish.py today. It was fun at first, but it is starting to get old. I do not mind other people using such fancy formatting, but it really is not my style. I tried something new though for a little more subtle in customization of text. I used one of the more standard scripts, text_replace.py, to replace all my lower-case esses with the character U+238E HYSTERESIS SYMBOL. The effect looked pretty cool, but on #Volatile, z was a bit of a spoilsport about it. Apparently, he uses broken software to connect to IRC. He uses a commend line client, and his command line is unable to display many glyphs even when his font supports them. Instead of accepting what I said repeatedly about how he could treat all "broken" characters that I say as esses, he insisted that my text was unreadable. Instead of admitting that the problem is on his end because he is using software that he knows to be broken, he insisted that I change my text back to normal. It was sad, but as usual, I try not to piss people off that do not actively antagonize me, so I went back to regular text. He tried to offer me the option of using lambda characters in some way (presumably U+03BB GREEK SMALL LETTER LAMDA [sic] shows up correctly for him), but that character really does not fit me. I do not think that he (or anyone else in the channel) realizes whey I chose U+238E HYSTERESIS SYMBOL. Furthermore, lambda characters seem too related to lambda functions in programming. These are functions without a true name and which cannot be easily reused. I do not use lambda functions. These are my thoughts on functions: If the function can be reused in other projects, it should have a proper name and not be a lambda function. If the function is project-specific and cannot really be reused, it should be a lambda function (or closure). If your function cannot be reused in other projects, you probably have not generalized it enough. While I support the existence of such language constructs as lambda functions and closures, I feel that in most cases, using them is the wrong way to go about things. They are like the eval language construct: the language should support it, but developers should avoid using it if at all possible.

While cleaning up, I found my mother's first ex-husband's high school diploma. Why does she even have this? Speaking of which, when I got my high school diploma, she insisted on "keeping it herself for a while", but it has been years and she still has not given mine back either. This does not bode well for my chances of ever seeing my diploma again.

My mother said that we would be returning on Saturday, but it is Saturday now, and she never showed. She must have changed the plan without telling me. I did not bring clean clothing to change into tomorrow. Maybe she will come tomorrow?

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Returning home

Day 00344: Sunday, 2016 February 14

Taking a break from cleaning, I set up a couple command aliases on WeeChat allow me to quickly turn on and off my automatic ess replacement. However, though this was not happening yesterday, esses in commands are being replaced too. While setting up these commands, I ended up having to shut off WeeChat so that I could manually edit the configuration and finish writing up my command aliases. Having found this new issue, I added an escape option to my ess replacement, both when automatic replacement is on and when it is off. When on, a backslash before the ess causes it to remain a simple ess and not be replaced. When off, a backslash causes the simple ess to be converted to U+238E HYSTERESIS SYMBOL. The aliases, if anyone wants them, can be set up in WeeChat with the following commands. Make sure that you add both aliases before running /on though.

/alias on set plugins.var.python.text_replace.replacement_pairs "s=⎎,\⎎=s"
/alias off set plugins.var.python.text_replace.replacement_pairs "\s=⎎"

On #Volatile, whitanne showed me that there is a Debian mirror in onion space! There is no time now, but I need to switch to using this mirror when I get a chance. Apparently, more than just privacy went into the decision to set up this mirror. Attackers knowing when security patches have been installed on your machine was a concern that could not be fixed using basic TLS. Simply put, TLS would obscure the details of what exactly you downloaded from the Debian repositories, but it would not obscure the size, which could be compared against the package sizes of new security updates.

By the end of the night, I was starting to panic. The thing that you have to understand is that I suffer from extreme paranoia. I quite literally trust no one. If I say that I trust you, I do not mean that in any literal sense, I simply trust you a little more than other people, but still not much at all. My mother had not showed yesterday, she did not seem to be showing today, and my father had already driven off with Vanessa and Cyrus. Typically, my mother wants to beat them home to be there to welcome them. I happened to sit down at my computer for another break though, and saw that Vanessa and Cyrus were online in TorChat. I had a secure way to ask if our mother was at home! As it turns out, she was not, and later came to pick me up. She emailed before coming, though this was after the last time that I checked my computer, and she had failed to communicate the fact that I would be staying an extra day, so I was not expecting any email from her. I only learned about the email on the way home.

She complained that i had not yet thrown out one particular item, so I threw that out before we left, but otherwise did not seem as disappointed in my progress in cleaning the house as I am. I feel like I should have gotten more done.

Just as we were almost home, we saw a deer in the middle of the street and nearly smacked into it. It did not help that it was a very foggy night. We swerved and the deer was fine, but soon after, the van started a rhythmic and slight jerking, as if somethong was wrong with one of the wheels. Sure enough, when we checked, a decent-sized bolt or screw had been lodged deep within the tire. We are not sure if this tire is under warranty, so it might be expensive to fix.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

SNI

Day 00345: Monday, 2016 February 15

Ronsor and company are back! I have not seen them since Ronsor split his IRC network away from Volatile. It seems that he is now setting up his own IRC network. Soon though, he insisted that I turn of TLS and use the unencrypted port. I complied, though I will try using the encrypted port again next time that I connect. Multi-layer (Tor and TLS) encryption should not be discouraged.

One of the thoughts that kept me someone centered yesterday was the thought that my mother had to be home last night because she had to teach school this morning. She could not just take an extended trip without warning. However, it seems that there is no school today because of some holiday. That is disconcerting. I could have ended up at the old house for another day at least. I need to be more prepared next time.

I have been considering normalizing the spider's results using scheme-specific methods before displaying them, so I started reading the RFCs to learn how to do that. I found that contrary to what I had learned before, HTTPS scheme is defined identically to the HTTP scheme, with the exception of the default port. This means that HTTPS URIs should allow trailing dots in their domains while still being valid! A while back, I ran into a problem with the Apache Web Server throwing errors when asked to display an HTTPS website that used a trailing dot in the domain name. Asking for help, I was told that this is the correct behavior and that Web servers that do not do this are actually accepting invalid values. I was shown some sort of standards document that backed up this claim, too. I do not seem to be able to find such a document now though. My best guess is that I was actually shown a document relating to SNI. In SNI, trailing dots are not allowed. However, in HTTPS, URIs, the trailing dot is very much allowed. Furthermore, the HTTP Host header *must* match the authority component of the URI, including a trailing dot in the host if present, but not including the userinfo subcomponent or its @ delimiter. This means that if someone tries to access the URI https://example.com./, they Web browser is supposed to set the SNI name to example.com, but set the Host header to example.com.. These two values are not required to match one another, and in some cases such as this one, are required *not* to match one another.

Trying to insure that the error was most definitely client-side, not server side, I tried connecting using command line tools, both over localhost on cepo and remotely from newdawn. I found that cURL strips the trailing dot, both in the Host header and in the SNI name. On the other hand, Wget leaves the trailing dot in the Host header, but also mistakingly leaves it in the SNI hostname. With a bit of work, I was able to coax cURL into sending the correct Host header without making it send a malformed SNI hostname, allowing me to complete my test on Apache. Apache accepted the Host header with a trailing dot and the SNI hostname without one, and reported them correctly to the PHP instance running on that machine. I have modified my remote_files class to take a uri object instead of a string so that it may more easily access the host component, which it now uses to correctly set the Host header.

After fixing the remote_files class, I decided to test onion addresses with it on a whim. It worked! I was able to connect to connect to onion addresses with trailing dots in their host names. At first, I thought that the issue with Tor not allowing onion addresses to be fully-qualified was not an issue in Tor at all, but in the applications that run over Tor. I thought that the issue was related to SNI. I quickly realized that that was probably not the case, and that cURL was probably stripping the dot of the end of the host name before passing it to Tor, but by the time I had come to that realization, I had already asked on #Tor about it. There, they accused me of intentionally asking stupid questing in attempt to waste their time, citing my connections to wowaname as the reason for these accusations. In the past, I had heard that there are two ways to to tell your applications how to reach onion addresses over Tor. The correct way is to is to have the application use the SOCKS proxy to resolve names. The incorrect way, though it works, is to map individual onion addresses to a particular local IP address so that they are resolved by the machine outside of Tor. I forget what onion address is used, but I thought that Tor was resolving onion addresses to this same IP address on the fly. I tried resolving onion addresses with tor-resolve, hoping to try both the trailing-dot and no trailing-dot versions of addresses, but tor-resolve does not seem to be able to actually resolve onion addresses. Instead, it resolves standard DNS addresses Tor. Again, I asked about this in #Tor, and found that that SOCKS5 does not work that way. When using SOCKS5, applications do not try to resolve names before making connections. Instead, applications just pass the name to the proxy and the proxy does whatever it wants with the name. Onion addresses do not get "resolved" at all! Mapping onion addresses to a local IP address is instead used for transparent proxying.

Armed with my new understanding of HTTPS URIs and SNI, the next step is clear. I need to test several Web browsers and file bug reports against them, Wget, and cURL. I looked up a list of Web browsers for Debian, and noticed Midori on the list. The version of Midori that was in the Debian 7 repository was outdated and Midori was dropped entirely from Debian 8. It was honestly my favorite Web browser though, and it appears to be in the Debian 8 backports repository! Normally, I would be reluctant to add the backports repository to my source list, but this is the perfect opportunity to install Midori and use testing and bug report filing as an excuse to do so.

Before updating my source list to point to more sources, I thought that it would be a better idea to update my source list to use the onion address mirror of the sources that I already use. I ran into two issues. First, while the onion mirror is a drop-in "http://ftp.*.debian.org/debian/", there does not seem to be an onion-based replacement for the http://security.debian.org/ source. Second, when using torsocks, several error lines are output at the end of any call to aptitude that involves remote file retrieval. All identical, these error messages tell the current time, then say WARNING torsocks[13498]: [syscall] Unsupported syscall number 202. Denying the call (in tsocks_syscall() at syscall.c:165). From the looks of it, some system call is being blocked, potentially to prevent a data leak. While I do not want my package manager leaking data, the Debian group probably is not doing anything malicious. Likewise, if these system calls are being blocked, I do not know if it causes damage to the system, as it is not completeing every task that it has tried to when making system changes. I tried installing apt-transport-tor, and that seems to work, although it required changing all sources on my source list to use the unregistered tor: scheme in their URIs. No doubt, these system calls are still being made, but now successfully, so data may be being leaked. It is suboptimal, but it sounds like better integration with Tor is being worked on. As for the issue of an onion-based replacement for http://security.debian.org/, that will have to wait as well. I was going to make a comment on the article about the mirror asking if there is currently a replacement for http://security.debian.org/, but posting a comment requires an OpenID account, which I have not yet set up. Dealing with reporting Web browser bugs is more important to me right now. Web browsers failing to send correct SNI host names is hindering my ability to use the fully-qualified version of my domain and still expect to be visible on the Internet.

With that out of the way, I added the backports repository. There was not time tonight to test out a ton of Web browsers, but I was excited to get to try Midori again, so I installed that. Unfortunately, Midori does not support SOCKS proxies, so I have to use torsocks with it, but I was not able to get any definitive results, at least at first. Midori was unable to store "pinned certificates", so it was unable to ignore the certificate mismatch caused by the trailing dot on the domain I was testing with. Because the error message mentioned the GNOME keyring, I decided to try setting Xfce to start GNOME-compatibility services at startup, then restarted my Xfce session. This worked, but resulted in the server throwing an error, indicating that Midori is sending invalid SNI host names.

I love Midori because of its clean interface and the fact that it displays the correct URI in the address bar, unlike most modern Web browsers. However, it seems that the updates have not prevented Midori from crashing as it when I last used it.

Turning on GNOME-compatibility services seems to have messed up SSH key decryption pass phrase entry. SSH no longer asks for the pass phrase on the command line. Instead, it pops up an annoying pinentry-like prompt for pass phrase entry. Annoyingly, this box does not allow autotyping. However, it does allow pasting, so it is still usable. This same prompt seems to have replaced the pinentry prompt used to input PGP key pass phrases as well, and might actually be some alternate mode of pinentry. If it is though, it does not explain why pinentry is not intercepting the SSH pass phrase entry prompt.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

HTTPS and IRCS

Day 00346: Tuesday, 2016 February 16

Further experimentation showed me that Midori does not support modern styling options. My weblog index displays one calendar page on top of another, all the way down. If a Web browser supports flex boxes, calendar pages are instead displayed one next to another, only creating multiple rows as needed to prevent a need for horizontal scrolling. This is beyond the scope of my bug testing, but means that making Midori my Web browser of choice again is not really an option. My fallback option, simple centering of the calendar pages, functions perfectly and the page looks as good as it can without fixed widths or flex boxes, but I need something with modern rendering features on which to develop.

Next, I tried Arora. Arora has working SOCKS5 proxy support, so I did not have to rely on torsocks. Arora seems to send the incorrect SNI server name like the others. It displays the correct address in the address bar like Midori, but also like Midori, it does not seem to have support for CSS flex boxes.

After that, I tried Chromium. I already knew that Chromium would refuse to work with torsocks and has no built-in way to set a proxy, so I would have no way to do any testing. However, I thought that I had better check, just in case that this issue had been fixed. As it turns out, Google still refuses to provide a graphical way to set a proxy and refuses to provide a way to set a proxy that will be used every time that the Web browser starts. However, Chromium now has a command line method of setting the proxy for only a single session. By running chromium --proxy-server=socks5://localhost:9050, you can start up the Web browser and have it use Tor until you close it. My guess is that many people complained about not being able to set a proxy in Chromium without setting a system-wide proxy for all non-Chromium applications and/or not being able to set a proxy in Chromium on a system that does not have system-wide proxy settings, so Google sort of halfway complied. They made it possible to use a proxy, though they made it highly inconvenient as you have to specify command line options every time that you start the Web browser. This also means that opening Web browser from another application, such as by clicking on a link in an email, will bypass the proxy as the command line option will never be specified. Like the other Web browser though, Chromium is sending malformed SNI host names.

Epiphany seems to lack proxy settings, but at least it works with torsocks. It too is sending malformed SNI host names. Am I seriously the only person that has run across this issue? I would have thought that at least some Web browsers would get this right. Konqueror also has SOCKS5 support and sends malformed SNI host names. Conkeror will not even start, so I cannot test it. NetSurf has no SOCKS proxy support, but works with torsocks. However, it uses invalid normalization of host names in URIs, so the trailing dot is removed before making a request, not only in SNI host names as it should be, but also in the address bar and Host header like it should not be. Surf does not seem to have any configuration menus with which to set a proxy, but it works with torsocks, though it still sends malformed SNI host names. I cannot seem to get uzbl to accept work over torsocks and I cannot find any proxy settings. Elinks does not seem to be SOCKS proxy-compatible, but it works with torsocks. However, it does not seem to be able to reach onion addresses. Furthermore, it does not send SNI server names and incorrectly strips the trailing dot off of the Host header. Links sends the correct Host header, but does not send an SNI host name either. Links2 seems to have the same behavior as Links. Lynx does not seem to have proxy settings, but works through torsocks. Again though, it cannot connect to onion addresses. It sends valid SNI indormation, but this may be because it incorrectly strips the trailing dot off of the host entirely, as it does incorrectly remove the trailing dot from the Host header. Lastly, I tried w3m. This browser has a -no-proxy flag that can be specified, though I cannot see any options to actually set a proxy for this flag to bypass. Torsocks works, and allows access to onion addresses. However, w3m does send malformed SNI host names.

Work on Web browser testing got cut short. I suppose that I was dune with the testing itself, but I did not get time to sort the Web browsers into bug severity level and file bug reports against the Web browsers that I felt that I might be able to have an impact on. Instead, The Unknown Man started talking about IRC servers again, so that became the more pressing issue. He is already thinking about names for his network, the current consideration being "V0rtex", apparently spelled with a zero. This makes his server and mine unable to join together, as I had already been planning to call my network "s" (not that The Unknown Man knew that). Due to the nature of IRCS URIs, if I could get my network, called s, to be generally recognized as being the network by that name, my network would be reachable via the URIs ircs://s/, irc://s/, and irc6://s/, making it reachable by some of the shortest IRC URIs available. The specification does seem to allow use of the empty string as a host name, though that seems like it would cause more interoperability problems than it is worth. Likewise, it would make it hard to refer to the network by name. Of course, I will still use the URI formed using the fully-qualified domain name, as that is the most interoperable of all, even though it will be a longer URI. Even if we do not link servers, I want the reason to be something other than the fact that I do not have mine up yet, so I need to get mine up and running.

I wanted to use ngIRCd simply because I know that it works and is easy to set up, but I decided that the approach that would work better in the long run is to open up the channel name space as much as possible by choosing an IRC daemon that would support the most channel types. The two IRC daemons on Wikipedia's comparison list said that the two daemons that support the four main channel types were IRCD and miniircd, but the list also said that these two daemons could not link to other servers using encrypted links. Encryption is much more vital than channel types, so once again, I found myself looking at daemons that support three major channel types, a class in which ngIRCd is the only member of on the list. I updated cepo's repository list to use the onion address and apt-transport-tor, performed an overdue system update, then installed ngIRCd.

Getting ngIRCd to bind to port 994, the default for URIs of the ircs: scheme, was no easy task. In the end, I found that the daemon was being started as root, but was dropping its privileged status and running as an unprivileged user *before* binding to any ports. On first glance, this appears to be an oversight by the developer, but it turns out that this was done deliberately. Po||ux of #ngIRCd explained that he programmed ngIRCd to drop privileges first because of the rehashing feature that he built. This feature allows ngIRCd to reload its configuration and adjust itself to match without actually restarting. If it bound to ports before dropping root privileges, reloading the configuration would cause the daemon to inexplicably lose access to any low-numbered ports. This inconsistency would be the real bug. The sucky part though is that when ngIRCd drops root privileges, it seems to drop all extra privileges granted by the setcap command as well. For hours, I tried using this command, showed to me by teatime of #Debian, to try to give the daemon access to the low-numbered ports with the CAP_NET_BIND_SERVICE flag. However, after much effort and the help of someone that prefers not to be mentioned by name, I found that as long as the daemon was started as root, setcap had no effect. It seems that if the daemon is not run as root, it is unable to shed the permissions granted by setcap. Po||ux showed me that copying /lib/systemd/system/ngircd.service to /etc/systemd/system/ngircd.service and editing the copy, one can add a "User={desired user}" line and the daemon will be started as that user. I now have ngIRCd running on the default ports used by the ircs: and irc: URI schemes, ports 994 and 6667, respectively. As I can only run the server over an onion for now, this learning experience could have waited, but I really did not want to set up a daemon now that I was not sure that I would be able to use once I was back on the clearnet. I have forwarded the correct onion ports to their respective clearnet ports, and tomorrow, I will work on finding the default ports used by clients so that I can forward those as well.

I received a letter from the local community college by post today. They asked me to go through an online orientation, but also said that they had sent me the same thing by email. I checked my email inbox though, and they had sent nothing! I logged into my community college account to make sure that they had the correct email address for me. As it turns out, they had decided to assign me a new email address, but as an added bonus, they told me nothing about this new inbox so I have not been receiving any emails from them even when they send them. They also did not offer an option for me to change my email address to my prefered one, so I needed to set up access to the email account that they had assigned me. The school email accounts are unfortunately hosted by Microsoft, so I needed to log in through them. As soon as I logged in with the idiotic, insecure, and easily guessable numeric password that the school had assigned me based on my data of birth, Microsoft insisted that I change my password to something more reasonable. However, they would not accept any password that I chose! They just kept insisting that my password needed to be at least eight characters long and contain characters from at least three of four character classes: upper-case letters, lower-case letters, digits, and non-alphanumeric characters. Unless told to do otherwise, I always use twenty-five character passwords that contain characters from all four classes of character, so there should not have been a problem. I tried several passwords and even tried dropping the non-alphanumeric characters under the premise that perhaps Microsoft was actually choking on some of those characters. In the end, I ended up typing by hand the idiotic password "qweRTY123$%^", checking to see if Microsoft was detecting the fact that I was pasting the passwords and did not like that. That password worked! I of course went in to the settings to change the password again, but there, I got the real answer. In the settings, it says that the passwords cannot be longer than sixteen characters. The previous page had kept telling me about the lower bound, but did not mention anything about there even being an upper bound! Microsoft, as usual, expects users to be idiots without mentioning such, and expects users to not use passwords with any real length to them.

Speaking of email accounts assigned by schools, when I managed to get back my account at my old school, I was also able to get back my school email account there. (The other school also assigned me an email account, but they both told me that that email account existed and sent most emails to my preferred email address instead of the school-assigned email address.) This account is unfortunately hosted by Google, but I logged in anyway today so that I could download my old emails for archival. I tried to log in with my email client, but I was told that the password was bad. I tried logging in through the Web interface to reset the password, but that did not work either. The client still could not connect. Finally, I noticed a new email from Google through the Web interface. Google had blocked access to my account due to my client "not meeting security standards". Of course, Google did not mention what standards were not being met or how my client was not meeting them, so I had no way to find a client that would be considered secure. The email provided a link to an article about the topic, but again, the article only mentioned that I should upgrade to a more secure client and did not provide any clues as to what Google considers to be insecure. The article also explained how to disable the security feature. Trying to meet Google's "security standards" without any clue as to what those standards are is not feasible, so I just disabled the security feature and connected my client.

I started the school's online orientation, but there was just not enough time in the day to complete it with everything else that has happened today.

Ronsor has sstarted doing funky things with ports on his IRC server. At first, it was very confusing. It seemed that users on one port could see users in the user list that connected on their own port as well as users connected on the other port, but users connected on the other port could only see users that were connected on their own port. As it turns out, each port was running a different IRC server and some sort of strange relay system was relaying messages to the other servers. The messages were not coming through any sort of relay bot though, they were seeming to come directly from the server in the form of messages from users that did not exist. The reason that some users appeared to be on both user lists is simply that these users were logged into both ports/servers.

Wowaname told me about her new Git server today. As it is running Gogs, it should have a familiar interface, as NotABug.org uses Gogs as well. I asked about running Git over Tor, and wowaname said to run Git over SSH, as SSH is SOCKS-friendly. Apparently proxying is set on a per-host basis though, with wildcard support. I could send everything through Tor by using the host *, but then all connections to hosts using the //test. and //local. TLDs will get proxied too, so I will not be able to connect to my local server. I will probably look into this and set that up as time allows. If necessary, I can always proxy on a per-TLD basis and add configuration for all known TLDs, though if I can instead just add configuration for these two TLDs that overrides the main proxy configuration, that would be the easiest and most forward-comparable way to do this.

It seems that my mother now wants me to become an aid at her school. That does not sound fun, but if it worked out, it would both be a job to help pay off my school loans and a way to put off school a bit longer while I attempt to pay off those loans. I am really not comfortable going back to school before I finish paying off my loans and have saved up enough money to go back to school without taking out any more loans.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.1 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

IRC

Day 00347: Wednesday, 2016 February 17

I've come to the conclusion that my obsession with short names is counterproductive to setting up an IRC network for several reasons. First and foremost, I need allies more than I need a great name. The Unknown Man and I seem to agree on a lot of things as to how the network should be run. If I can play my strengths and he his, we should have a better chance of success than either of us would alone. The Unknown Man beat me to being prepared, so if that means that he gets to pick a cool-sounding name instead of me getting to pick a single-character name, that seems more than fair. Furthermore, my obsession with short names makes no sense, given the current context. When dealing with domain names, there is a length limit. Simply put, a short domain name technically has more subdomains than a long domain name. In practice, this does not mean a whole lot, as even the longest possible second- or even third-level domains has many more times the number of subdomains than there exist IPv4 and IPv6 addresses combined. If you have a domain, there may not be enough disk space or computing power in the world to host unique content and/or services at every one of your subdomains, assuming that you do not host something such as a dynamic Web page that generates content based on the domain name used to access the page. However, I find the extended range of subdomains to be rather symbolic of the open possibilities, possibilities that I'd be cutting myself off from by insisting on using such a short network name. Besides, network names do not have "sub-names". Only the single name would be used, and only really in URIs. As URIs do not seem to suffer from a length limit, as I said above, my obsession is out of context here. And that is not to mention the fact that the URI that makes use of the short name would only really work if we actually became known by our official name of "s". More likely, if our address even gets bundled in IRC clients at all, we would become known as "s network", "s-net", or something else that is not just a single letter. The name "V0rtex" sounds much better, is easier to recognize, is more likely to catch on, and is more likely to lead us to actually becoming a major network. There is little change that we actually *will* become a major network, but I should not be imposing strange restrictions that do nothing but hinder our chances.

Speaking of strange restrictions, I am going to try to convince The Unknown Man that we should keep our ports 994 and 6667 open to users if at all possible. He wants to rent server resource, so I don't know if the hosting company will allow use of port 994 to begin with. Furthermore, they use one of the BSD systems, I forget which one, so the things I learned about making it work on that system may not apply, even if the hosting company allows it. I will say this: it is a good thing that I chose to use ngIRCd yesterday, as that is the daemon that The Unknown Man and I had discussed using before. If it wasn't, I would need to uninstall it and set up the other daemon.

I set up the onion ports 6697 and 9999 to forward to local port 994, so now TLS connections are available on all three ports.

I found that my school email account comes with a SIP account. Of course, this account cannot be trusted because it is hosted and run by Microsoft, but maybe it means that the school is willing to contact and be contacted via SIP. I haven't seen a SIP address on their website, so probably not, but it is worth asking about if I end up going to school there. When I find the time, I need to get my own SIP account set up under my own domain.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Better spider debugging and list-based navigation

Day 00348: Thursday, 2016 February 18

Today, I checked in on the spider and found that it was about a week into working on the current website, had about an estimated week left, and had crashed. A week's worth of crawling efforts had been lost, and if I could find and fix the bug, it would take about a week to reach that page again to test the fix. Because of this, I set up a new feature that allows the administrator to specify a URI to test on. Because of how the spider works, the specified URI will be used third, right after the robots.txt and main index pages. It still means a lot less waiting and a lot less wasted effort. It appears that there was no bug for me to fix though, I had already fixed it and the page that the spider choked on before was no longer an issue. Most likely, I'd fixed this but hadn't restarted the spider to make the fix come into effect due to the fact that restarting the spider would cause the spider to lose its progress on the current site.

My initial plan was to implement the feature in such a way that if a debugging URI is provided, *only* that page would be loaded and parsed. I was going to do this by having the debug switch set the queue variable to an object of a class that acted like an array, but just dropped any information given to it. However, it seems that even the most array-like object implementing all the relevant interfaces cannot be passed to \array_pop(), so after building that class, I ended up throwing it out.

It turns out that the reason that the atheme-services package in Debian is so outdated isn't because the Debian package maintainers for that package stopped caring or have been too busy. It is because the Atheme team has requested that distribution maintainers only package their long-term support version! The copy in the Debian repositories is the latest long-term support version. It's a shame that this version doesn't support ngIRCd. I'll have to use a copy from outside the Debian repositories, which is something that I really don't like doing when choosing server software.

Speaking of IRC, I forgot that The Unknown Man and I had agreed to only allow encrypted connections to our network. Yesterday, I wrote about URIs with the irc: and irc6: schemes, but those won't really be relevant to our network.

Someone that prefers not to be mentioned by name has requested that I provide an index for my weblog that uses lists instead of ASCII calendars. He thinks that they would be more accessible in text-based Web browsers than the ASCII calendars. I disagree, but agreed to set up such an index. After agreeing to build such an index, I realized that while I still disagree that it will help in text-based Web browsers, it might actually be helpful for blind people using screen readers. With that in mind, I also added a title attribute to the links on the calender-based index page. I added both an ascending and descending list of entries.

While trying to set up the set up the list-based version of the index, I ran into a problem that I have run into countless times before. The list has an order, so unordered lists are the incorrect thing to use semantically, but ordered lists don't work either because they stupidly index from one. If only I could use the start attribute! However, that attribute is deprecated in XHTML 1.1, the latest version of the XHTML standard, or so I thought. I looked into it today to see it XHTML5 is any closer to finalization, and it seems that it was finalized over a year ago. According to one article, it took eight years to finalize it. No wonder I gave up checking on it! I had kind of started wondering if XHTML5 would ever become an actual standard.

It seems that Links, the Web browser that my friend uses, does not handle lists correctly. If you attempt to list from zero, Links uses bullet points instead of numbers. If you use a reverse list, Links will still count up instead of down. I never could find a solution to either issue. The problem with the reversed lists might be that they are a newish feature. However, list starting points are old enough that they have become deprecated and then undeprecated. There is no good reason not to support them fully. Thankfully, I found a workaround. It isn't as good as using the the start attribute of the <ol/> tag, but you can also use the value attribute of the <li/> tag.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

More spider enhancements

Day 00349: Friday, 2016 February 19

I finished my school orientation today. I will probably send in the feedback tomorrow.

I looked into becoming a school aid as my mother wanted me to, but the school had no such job openings listed.

I received the first of my two tax refund checks in the mail today. I will probably go to the bank on Monday. As my current bank appears to order marked bills to be destroyed, I will look into getting an account at another bank in the area. I've had an account with them in the past though, and last time, they charged a ridiculous fee for using my debit card in one of the local stores. This time, I will ask more specifically about fees, though I don't use a debit card any more, especially in person. I much prefer cash. Online, I use my credit card, though that has my real name on it. Unless the bank is willing to issue me a card under my real name instead of my legal name, I won't be using a card from that bank at any time.

I made a couple enhancements to the spider today. First, I accounted for an issue that I have been worried about lately because of all the crashing. Namely, it has been over a month since I first started the spider, the spider is configured to recrawl sites after a month has passed, and the spider was programmed to crawl sites in alphabetical order. The first sites to be crawled before were starting to be recrawled before some sites had been crawled at all! I've changed the order in which crawling occurs. Now, the spider crawls sites in an order based on the last time that the site has been crawled. The later the latest crawl was, the later that site ends up in the queue. Sites that have never been crawled are now first in the queue. Second, I fixed a bug in TLS-handling. Previously, the spider would allow "untrusted" certificates, but only if those certificates were issued to that site. Whether "trusted" or "untrusted", certificates would be rejected if used on a different website than the one listed in the certificate. That means that if a certificate was self-signed, it would be accepted, but if it was issued to example23example.onion but used on subdomain.example23example.onion, the certificate would be rejected, whether the certificate was self-signed or signed by a known "authority". Until we have a mechanism for enabling encryption without implying an identity, I cannot honestly say that there is any value is paying attention to any identifying information on unknown sites, especially when doing something that does not involve trust, such as Web crawling. Besides, the onion addresses themselves are proof of site ownership. If you have the onion key, you own that onion address and that is all the identity information that we need. I have fixed this, and TLS is now used by the spider only for encryption, so any certificate will work. I also found <javascript:/> in the spider's database, despite the fact that that URI doesn't include a domain, let alone an onion-based domain. I'm not sure how that address ended up in the database, as the spider is supposed to filter away all URIs that do not relate to onion space. Furthermore, I have been unable to replicate the error. My guess is that it had something to do with a bug I ran into on the fifth, though I must have fixed the bug without knowing at some point.

I found that the \DOMDocument class is exhibiting strange behavior in regards to dealing with the <base/> tag. I'm not sure if it handles absolute href values correctly, but it handles a value of / in an inconsistent manor. If the value is /, used, the parser considers the base URI of the document to be not a valid URI, but instead the system file path of the directory from which the script was run. It doesn't even use the directory that the script is in, but the script that the working directory that you were in when you started the script, so the results are different depending on what you have been doing. I decided to make sure that only absolute URIs may be legally used in the <base/> tag, but I actually found the reverse. The URI specified in the <base/> tag is normalized against the document's retrieval URI. As the \DOMDocument class had no way to know what the retrieval URI was, it was doing the best that it could. All that I have to do to fix the issue is inform \DOMDocument of the document's URI. I tried setting $DOMDocument->documentURI before parsing the document, but that didn't work. I thought that this value would be used durring parsing, but instead, it is set during parsing. To get the desired effect, you must set this value after parsing but before using the parsed data.

Lastly, I did some experimentation with retrieving information on cURL errors. Information on file transfers cannot be reliably retrieved, as any information that does not pertain to a given transfer will be returned with values from a previous transfer. Thankfully, testing shows that error handling is much more reliable. When the last transfer was a success, the error code is reset to zero and the error message is reset to an empty string. It could be that error handling was actually designed better than transfer information retrieval. However, I suspect that the more consistent behavior might be caused by something else. Success quite literally has an error code of zero, and the error strings are probably set by PHP based on error codes returned by cURL, not by cURL itself. It could very well be that success is implemented as an error case, so the new error overwrites the old error. However this works though, the important part to me is that it *does* work. Updating the spider to account for different types of errors should be trivial. I plan to groups the error codes into three categories. The first category will represent success, and will be handled as it is currently being handled. This includes both cases that cURL considers to be a success and cases in which an actual website was reached, but the page is considered bad, such as 404 and 500 HTTP errors. The second category will be that of failures, such as not receiving any response from the server. The third will just be a fallback group for errors that I failed to account for, and will kill the spider so that I can notice and fix the problem. In fact, perhaps this (mostly-)binary checking of errors should be added directly to my remote_files class.

My mother and I went out to collect bullet shells again, though most of the shells that we found were made of a metal that she doesn't care about, so we mostly gathered bullets instead. On the way there, she noticed that some movie that she hasn't seen in a long time is playing in a theater, so now she wants us to go see it on Sunday. The movie is older than I am, but it's proprietary and still under copyright. I'll probably spend the time contemplating what else needs to be done to improve the spider. We're going to spend tomorrow working in her classroom and doing some house cleaning so that her friend can come over on a later date.

I wrote to my carrier today about unlocking the device that they sold me. I only got that device because with the way that their system is set up, I'm paying for the device whether I actually get it or not. I might as well make them give me what I'm paying for, even if it's not the most useful thing ever. With the device unlocked, I'm now eligible for a new device, which supposedly will be here in two days. Of course, my Replicant is the device that I'll actually be using for anything that actually needs to be done.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Orbot onions and tox: URIs

Day 00350: Saturday, 2016 February 20

I've been very curious about hidden service hosting on a mobile. In particular, I wanted to know where the onion key for such a hidden service is stored by Orbot. So today, I decided to give in and give it a random onion address. I have tried assigning it one of my generated onion addresses, but I never got that working, so now, I allowed it to generate its own onion address. I found that if you use oandbackup to view and modify Orbot's files, the onion address will be located at "{decompressed directory}/org.torproject.android/app_data/hs{port that you specified}/private_key". Changing onion ports will cause Orbot to generate a new onion address, though the original one will not be deleted, it will only go dormant until the port is switched back. Unlike Ricochet, Orbot is not afraid to generate onion addresses without Internet access, so I was able to generate these onion addresses without causing any of them to go live. It should be very easy to swap out the onion for a more readable address if I ever decided to host a hidden service on my mobile.

Ronsor built a new encryption library called rcrypt. I'm not sure if there's any sort of security goal that he is trying to accomplish by building his own encryption algorithms, but I get the feeling that this is more of a project for fun than anything. I hope that he learns a lot from this project, though unless he is extremely good at securing encryption algorithms, rcrypt isn't going to become widely used. Still, it seems like fun to experiment with and encrypting alone is no fun, so I generated a set of keys myself. I need to get an encryption page up at some point, displaying the various public keys that I use, such as this new key, my PGP key, my SSH key, and because people ask for it sometimes, the hash of my TLS certificate. I might put the two onion addresses that I use there too, as onion addresses are a means of locating a particular public key for hidden service encryption.

I received a letter from the state today saying that they had amended my tax return and were giving me back more money than I had asked for. The issue had been that I had not applied for the kickback from last year because the tax-preparation site had been very confusing in regards to how to apply for that. In any case, the hilarious part is that the state said that I disagreed with them giving me this extra money, I could appeal to have them accept my original filed return instead. Though less funny, this notice that they sent came a day later than the actual check from them.

I've been considering installing Tox lately. It seems like a nice encryption-heavy and decentralized communication platform. However, they use an unregistered URI scheme for linking to chat handles on Web pages. This of course has no impact on whether or not I start using the software, but if they register their scheme, I'll actually post a link to my handle as well. Over the past few days, I've considered attempting to register the tox: scheme as a provisional scheme, but I decided that it would be better if I tried to talk the Tox developers into registering it themselves. They would have better control of it that way. I was going to post the suggestion as a feature request, but reading through the bug tracker, it was already there. The developers seemed to be planning to attempt to register the scheme after the protocol is more finalized. I didn't think that waiting was the best idea unless they planned on waiting to roll out support for such URIs in their software, but they had already rolled out support. From what I've been reading, URI schemes should not be turned loose outside of a closed test environment without being registered, even if only registered provisionally, so I decided to see if I could change their minds. The worst that would happen is that they would turn me down or ignore me, right? So I plead my case, citing three main reasons that they might want to consider a provisional registration now, and it seems that one of the developers is now looking into it!

While we did clean up around the house today, we ended up going to the beach instead of working in the classroom. I think that my mother was too weary of the place to set foot in there today. I can't really blame here. She spends nearly every day wrangling monsters in there.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

uTox, qTox, and Antox

Day 00351: Sunday, 2016 February 21

I added the Tox repository to my source list. The instructions given for doing so said to add the package apt-transport-https, but Aptitude does not seem to be Tor-compatible without apt-transport-tor and the pseudo-scheme tor:, so I just replaced the https: scheme with the tor: one instead of installing apt-transport-https. That seemed to work without issues. My guess is that apt-transport-tor tried to fetch the packages and package information over unencrypted HTTP, was redirected to HTTPS, and was able to successfully download from the HTTPS site. This means that either apt-transport-tor is able to download over HTTPS or the downloads occurred over a non-Tor channel. I'm hoping for the former.

Once I had the repository added, I found that uTox was not available! Both qTox and Toxic were available as alternatives, but neither sounded as good as uTox. qTox is Qt-based, and Qt-based applications tend to be too flashy for my testes. Not only that, but they require pulling in a bunch of Qt libraries that I don't otherwise need because my own Xfce desktop is GTK+-based. Toxic on the other hand is a command line application. For the most part, I prefer graphical applications. I asked in the support channel, and they said that they currently have no package maintainer, so there are no uTox packages in the main repository. Instead, I was told to change the "code name" component of my APT line to release. I assumed that the "code name" in deb tor://pkg.tox.chat/debian nightly jessie was nightly, so I tried changing that, and no repository was found. Thinking that someone had misremembered the name of the repository and seeing that the two available options were nightly and stable, I tried stable instead. This time, the repository was found, but uTox was still not present. That was when it occurred to me that the stupid non-numeric nickname given to distribution releases is sometimes referred to as a code name, and the repository seemed to have the directory structure to support changing that to release, so I made that change and uTox became available.

I looked more into Tox today and found that Tox's long, random, and unruly chat handles can be placed in DNS records, though I'm not sure if they can be linked to that way. At the very least, the DNS-enabled name could serve as link text and be there for anyone that needs to write down the name for later use. However, the page on ToxDNS does not mention the DNS record format or naming scheme and ToxDNS is known to be under-documented. It sounds like documentation might be available within the week though, but I have been known to be quite impatient. Using a combination of the groupbot@utox.org identifier found on the wiki page, the _tox subdomain mentioned by one of the ToxDNS implementations, and a bit of guesswork, I was able to piece together that the DNS record in use was the TXT record at groupbot._tox.utox.org and performed a DNS query to obtain the record format so I could apply that same format to a record within my own domain. However, the record was not recognized by uTox. I tried using the name groupbot@utox.org instead, but that didn't work either, so I decided to install and test on qTox. Neither name worked on qTox either, though qTox mentioned needing to make a connection outside of my proxy to look up the names, which I allowed. A bit later, I decided to ask about if the feature was even implemented yet, as the known-good data, groupbot@utox.org, was not working. I wanted to be as clear as possible, to I tried the handle in both clients to get the exact error messages. However, this time, the handle worked in both! I tried my own handle, laptop@y.st, and that worked as well. I have no idea what the problem had been, but it seems to have resolve itself.

I do wonder though about the connection made outside of the proxy. Is uTox able to resolve the name without bypassing the proxy, unlike qTox, or is it bypassing the proxy without permission? If the TXT records are indeed not able to be reached through a SOCKS proxy because SOCKS handle DNS itself, perhaps this is the issue with XMPP on my mobile. Perhaps the XMPP clients are unable to check for and resolve SRV records.

Now having the information needed to set up DNS records used by Tox, I decided to add that information to the wiki page on ToxDNS. After registering an account though, I found that regular users are not allowed to make changes. I would need to get special permission in order to be of any help. I could ask for permission, but that's not really my style. If they don't want help from random users, you can count me out.

Having now used both uTox and qTox, I think that I now prefer qTox. Despite being a Qt application, it at least is more featureful than uTox. It minimizes to the notification and has the option to automatically start upon logging into your computer (in fairness, uTox and any other application could be set to do this too from Xfce's Sessions and Startup application). However, both applications seem to be unable to properly handle the URIs mentioned on the wiki, despite it being stated that both clients support them.

Yesterday, I installed a strange upgrade for Orbot. It had a different package signature than usual, indicating that it had come from the Guardian Project repository instead of the main F-Droid repository and the user interface looked quite a bit different. Today though, while trying to set up the Tox repository, ran into issues. It seemed that Orbot was making the connection to the Tor network, but applications were unable to get through. Some testing indicated that orWall was to blame, as Orbot's transparent proxy mode seemed to allow applications to connect to the network. However, nothing had changed with orWall. I tried resetting its data and I tried reinstalling it, neither of which worked. I tried downgrading Orbot though, and that *did* work. I'm not sure what the new Orbot release does differently than the old one, but it doesn't seem to be compatible with orWall. Antox, the mobile version of Tox, doesn't seem to be able to handle ToxDNS, but it does seem to be able to ToxDNS, so I was unable to add laptop@y.st to my contacts for testing. Furthermore, uTox and qTox are acting wonky, so I wasn't able to add mobile@y.st from my laptop. I checked the DNS records from my command line, and they are reaching my laptop, so I'm not sure what the problem is. I'll have to try again tomorrow.

We worked on cleaning the house more today, then went to see that movie that I mentioned a few days ago. I spent the movie time thinking about Tox and DNS records. After that, we went to pick up more bullet shells and went to work in our mother's classroom. She wanted me to staple some papers together to form books for the students, but she got really weird and told me off about what stapler I chose to use. She later claimed that it was because she thought that that stapler didn't work, but that doesn't make sense for a couple of reasons. First of all, it's the same stapler I used last time that I stapled books together too and she knows that. Clearly, that stapler works when I use it, even if she wasn't lying about the fact that she can never get it to work. If it's true, she simply doesn't know how to work that stapler, which would be pretty sad seeing as it works just like any other stapler. Second, if the stapler really didn't work, there'd be nothing for her to get ticked off about. I'd simply try to use it, fail, then go get another stapler. It's worth noting for the record that after she got weird about the stapler, I did find it to be jammed, but this was only after. That might have been the reason that she thought that it didn't work, but still doesn't explain her getting angry with me. Likely, if it comes up again, she'll claim that she got angry because I wasted time unjamming it, but I only unjammed it after she had gotten strange, as I had only found that it had been jammed after she had gotten strange; I simply had not made it to the stapling part of the process yet as I was still folding all the papers in half. Our mother was also yelling at Vanessa earlier today because our mother was being unclear and Vanessa was not understanding what was being said, so it could be that our mother is on the down side of another one of her bipolar swings. I should try to tread lightly.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Volatile Git

Day 00352: Monday, 2016 February 22

When I awoke, I found that my mobile's battery was dead, despite having been mostly-charged when I went to bed. I plugged the mobile into the wall, but the battery drain was almost as quick as the charging process. My laptop also seemed to have much shorter battery life today. Tox is a real battery drainer! I ended up uninstalling it from the mobile and I won't run it on my laptop on autostart anymore, I'll run it only when I have a wall outlet to plug into and am actually at my machine.

The DNS record for my mobile's Tox instance seems to resolve now on uTox, but not on qTox. I find this very confusing, but as uTox and qTox seem to share profile information and contacts, it is possible to use one application to add contacts and the other to chat.

I stumbled upon another project, Ring. The people on Tox brought it up and called it a Tox clone. It looks like it might be useful, but it isn't something that I want to look into right now. It seems that I have so little time lately even for the things that I want to get done. If Ring had either a URI scheme or DNS support, it might attract my interest a bit more, but for now, I'll set it aside.

Someone that prefers not to be mentioned brought up an article about a problematic clause in CC BY 3.0. Supposedly they fixed it in version 3.01 of the license (a version that I can't even find), but I don't think that the new version of the clause does what they say that they want it to. Supposedly, they want the license to not grant the right to ignore the "moral rights" of the author, but instead, the license seems to enforce the author's "moral rights". That said, I don't think that this will be an issue in practice. Unlike the GFDL, which is intended to be proprietary, CC BY is intended to be free. The intent of the licensers and the authors of the license needs to be taken into account, as if no legal actions are taken, those clauses essentially don't exist. It's troubling to have that language in the license, but that is one of the two main free media licenses and ruling out all works under it severely cuts what media is even available. I am going to continue listening to music under this license, though I hope that sites such as Bandcamp upgrade to version four of the license.

I took a trip to Bank of America, the bank that I dislike because of strange fees that they've levied on me in the past. It's stupid for me to even consider getting an account with them, but I was going to do it anyway. Banner Bank, my current bank, is having marked bills destroyed, which is counterproductive to my stamping of all bills that pass through me. However, Bank of America has sold all its branches that are even remotely local to Bank of the Cascades! The nearest branch that they have left is in Eugene, which isn't exactly within walking distance of my home any more. I could start an account with Bank of the Cascades, but they said that during this transitional period, new accounts cannot be created. I think that they said that new accounts will once again be available on the seventh of next month, but I had lots of coins that I needed to get rid of as I have no good place to store them and they were filling up both of my wallets. Next, I tried the other local bank, US bank. They, however, charge poor people a fee for being poor; there's a minimum account balance that one must meet to avoid this fee every month. Out of reasonably-distanced options, I went back to my current bank and deposited both the tax refund check and my piles of coins. I will try Bank of the Cascades again in two weeks if my second tax refund check has arrived.

While I was out today, it seems that I missed my package from the mobile company; it required a signature. The delivery people left a note saying that they would try again tomorrow. I guess that I should have postponed my trip to the bank until after I had the package, but I had no idea that it was coming today. Oh well, I'll wait at home tomorrow.

Ronsor released a JavaScript version of rcrypt today. Now certificates can be viewed or even created from within a Web browser. Again, when I get time, I need to set up a Web page with my public keys. Encryption keys aren't doing me any good when no one knows what they are to use them when communicating with me.

On #Volatile, z was asking me why my code is not up on Volatile Git. I had been meaning to get my code backed up there, but I've been so busy with other things lately. Seeing as I would be using Volatile Git's onion address, I first needed to get my SSH proxy set up so that I would even be able to push my online repositories through Git. Wowaname said that faye might be able to help, so I asked faye about setting SSH up to proxy all connections except those that are made to hosts on one of two specific TLDs, those used for local connections and that need to resolve DNS locally: //local. and //test.. As it turns out, I need to start reading the manual. Usually, I just use the --help argument passed to a given command instead, as it provides quicker and more concise information. However, this is only good when figuring out what arguments to pass in. When modifying configuration files, the information in the manual is more relevant. The configuration lines to add to ~/.ssh/config are simply these:

Host * !*.local local !*.test test
	ProxyCommand socat - socks4a:127.0.0.1:%h:%p,socksport=9050

With my Tor-enabled SSH connection up, I set up my account at Volatile Git. As I was uploading to a new repository, I took the opportunity to change the name of my spider from OnionSearch to OnionSpider. Originally, the plan was to create an actual search engine, but I just don't have the resources to run an actual search engine, and downgraded the project to only find onion-based services instead of additionally indexing all found pages. I changed the repository name on my NotABug.org account, then uploaded everything that I have on my NotABug.org account to my Volatile Git account, aside from one repository that I've been meaning to delete but still haven't. I've noticed that while NotABug.org lower-cases letters in it's Git repository addresses used for cloning (though not thee Web address), Volatile Git is better at preserving case. However, both the hidden service and clearnet service provide Git repository addresses that use the clearnet address. As Volatile Git runs on Gogs, I sould propably file a bug report against Gogs when I get time.

Tonight, my mother explained the reason that her friend will be staying over for a while. Apparently, there is a Geocaching event in the area that the two will be attending together. My mother has now invited me, but I'm not going to fall for that trap. I hate my legal name, preferring instead to use my real name, but if I use anything but my legal name in the presence of people that she interacts with, she freaks out. Thankfully, it seems that she wasn't expecting me to take her up on the invitation, and only offered in an effort to be nice.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Jeb Bush is out of the running. One down and two to go!

Day 00353: Tuesday, 2016 February 23

My sister brought to my attention that Jeb Bush has dropped out of the running for president! This is fantastic news. Bush said that if he became president, he would reverse the net neutrality decision, making him a huge threat to the Internet. However, there are still horrible people running that need to be defeated, either before or during the election. Donald Trump claims that he will lock down the Internet if elected. This threat is very vague, but still ominous. Furthermore, his racist ideals are certainly no good for our country. Hillary Clinton, on the other hand, has teamed up with Monsonto. We don't need a president that is in debt to that evil corporation. Clinton also has proved that she cannot be trusted by hiding her government-related emails from both the government and the public. One down, two to go!

A user on Tox posted an interesting link. I had thought that there were to equally-valid ways of dealing with copyright issues. The first method, and the one I use, is to avoid nonfree works. In doing so, I can put my energy into supporting artists and developers that don't try to oppress fans and users. The second strategy is to disregard copyright. This strategy is illegal, but if everyone did it, copyright would be essentially meaningless. Copyright wouldn't even hold up in court because jurors wouldn't convict over something that they themselves do. However, is seems that in practice, copyright infringement is a bad idea. Research suggests that piracy of the Windows operating system is hindering the adoption of Linux. There's no reason why this effect would be isolated to Windows and Linux. Other software and media are likely effected by this as well. This means that we should probably avoid nonfree works of any kind if it can at all be helped. Piracy is not the answer, using free software and media is!

Marc With a C sent out another letter about Unicorns Get More Bacon. If you haven't bought it already, his mystery bonus offer is still going.

I received my new voter registration card in the mail today. The thing is though, I still haven't updated my voter registration information yet. My guess is that this happened because I sent in that change of address form with the post office. They likely assumed that I'd also want my voter registration information updated and did that automatically. I still need to actually send in my voter registration update at some point though to change my political party, but not at the moment. There's too much to do right now and it could be useful being registered with the wrong party for the time being. I can vote against Trump in the primary elections this way.

My new mobile came in the mail today. As I said previously, it's not one that I'll use for anything but experimentation, but as I'm already paying for it in my monthly bill, I might as well actually get the thing. I was disgusted to find that the battery of the device could not be removed though! This means that if the battery ever goes dead, you have to replace the entire device. That's just idiotic. However, unlike my last device from them, you can actually disable Google Play Services, which among other things, both helps with privacy and fixes the error in which Google Play Services keeps crashing due to other Google applications having been disabled. However, not all of the Google applications can be disabled on this device. Google made sure to prevent the Google search application from being disabled.

Speaking of mobile devices, Cyrus found one on the way home from school today. He kept calling different contacts on the device looking for someone that could put him in touch with the owner until he managed to actually call the owner, who apparently had borrowed someone else's device. They seemed pretty happy to get the thing back.

It's been quite a while since I've heard from The Unknown Man. I'm starting to wonder when he will be in reach again.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

ICANN's ridiculous telephone number requirement

Day 00354: Wednesday, 2016 February 24

This morning, I awoke to find that my laptop battery is no longer charging beyond eighty percent. I was able to get the battery indicator to show a full charge by restarting newdawn, but it appears that the full battery indication is a ruse. The battery's charge still no longer lasts for even a full hour. My guess is that restarting the machine reset the charge level that the machine thinks is the maximum, but the battery has indeed become damaged.

I finally found a page on the ICANN website explaining the requirements for data in whois records. It seems that the reason that a telephone number is required while a fax number is only optional is due to ICANN wording, not registrars assuming that not everyone has a fax number and letting them off the hook on that requirement. I figured that it was ICANN wording, but I never could find the language used. For reference, the offensive stipulations that require a telephone number are below:

3.3.1.7 The name, postal address, e-mail address, voice telephone number, and (where available) fax number of the technical contact for the Registered Name; and

3.3.1.8 The name, postal address, e-mail address, voice telephone number, and (where available) fax number of the administrative contact for the Registered Name.

A while back, I located a potential back door for registering a domain under one of a few common gTLDs without having a telephone number and without giving inaccurate information. Basically, there's a registry that appears no to validate the telephone number field, so you can enter "I have no telephone service.", and they seem to accept it. There's a couple potential issues though, issues that i was aware of even when I first found it. Specifically, without attempting to register one of these domains, I can't be sure that the registry wouldn't reject the registration sent by the registrar. Even though the registrar isn't validating the data, the registry would still need to accept the input for this back door to even work. Second, if someone complained about your whois records, you could have your domain revoked, even if you honestly don't have a telephone number to provide. However, I did a bit more looking today, comparing prices. It seems that due to the high prices charged by this registry, it's really not worth it anyway. The //st. registry's prices are lower and they don't even ask for a telephone number.

I've done some thinking about the need to meet the ridiculous telephone number requirement too. I've come to the conclusion that in regards to my main domain, I need to do everything by the books. I cannot give anyone any ammunition to use against me and get my main domain revoked. For that reason, it makes perfect sense that I should stick with the //st. registry. However, auxiliary domains are lest important. If I lose my main domain, I lose my voice and my Internet presence, but if some jerk gets my service-providing domain revoked and I still have a voice, I can and will raise a ruckus and draw attention to the fact that the telephone number requirement is ridiculous and that not everyone has a telephone number to provide. However, I doubt that there will actually be any issue if I take two minor precautions. First, I would need to get whois privacy, preferably gratis whois privacy provided by a decent registrar as part of the domain registration. If gotten through Gandi, the whois records can still reflect my legal name, making me the legal owner, unlike with regular whois privacy. Second, I would need to set the telephone number seen by my registrar to be the exact same telephone number shown in the whois records. This accomplishes two feats. First, the registrar reaches their own privacy system if they try to call. Second, if they decide to revoke the whois privacy without my consent, they are exposing the same telephone number that was already exposed. If possible, it would be nice to set this telephone number correctly during the initial registration, so I'll try to figure out what their whois privacy telephone number is before registration.

I realized today that I shouldn't file a bug report against Gogs. When there are two clearnet domains in use to reach the same Gogs instance, it doesn't matter which domain is used to push to anf pull from repositories. The only time it makes a difference is when an onion domain and a clearnet domain are used to reach the same instance. However, the onion domain's ports might not be forwarded correctly to allow both Web access and SSH access. There might be only one domain that allows SSH access, so using a dingle domain in the interface instead of using a domain dynamically chosen based on which domain is used to access the Web interface is not a bug.

I received a letter by post today saying that I have been approved for state-issued health insurance coverage. There was information included about what to do if I want to have a hearing to contest their decision to cover me, but there was no insurance card included and no information on how to get the insurance card. Maybe they will send that later? In any case, coverage has been back dated to the first of December.

Checking in on the spider's progress, I found that it now estimates that it requires over five more months to complete its work on the current website due to how many pages it has. I won't even be in this house in five months! The spider is going to end up losing months worth of data collection efforts.

Still worrying about the effects of invalid and missing SNI host names, I decided to look into how to get the Apache Web Server to reject requests that do not make use of SNI. I found that Apache rejects requests in which the SNI host name does not match the host name specified in the Host header. I tested this information out and found it to be accurate. Even domains with trailing dots work as expected as long as the SNI host name isn't malformed. For example, if the SNI host name is example.com, it will function in combination with Host headers reading example.com or example.com., but not with Host headers reading example.net. Furthermore, there is a way to set up Apache to require that Web browser use SNI by setting the SSLStrictSNIVHostCheck directive to on. However, my experiments showed that this directive is ignored unless multiple virtual hosts exist on the same IP address/port combination. Basically, if you use the VirtualDocumentRoot directive to dynamically set up sites like I do, you'll need to set up a second dummy VirtualHost in order to make the SSLStrictSNIVHostCheck directive have any effect. That worked out okay though, as I decided to also block clients that fail to send a Host header. I configured the dummy VirtualHost to take connections in which there was no Host header, showing a default site. After doing some further thinking though, I decided to allow clients without SNI support to access the real website. The thing is, lack of SNI support causes the Web server to potentially send the incorrect TLS certificate. This will either cause the Web browser to complain (seems to be common in graphical clients) or the Web browser will ignore the fact that the wrong certificate was sent (seems to be common in text-based clients). Why should I care? The client is causing the problem itself and the issue doesn't even effect me. It's not the same as when a client sends invalid SNI host names and I have to avoid producing URIs without trailing dots on the domains to avoid issues. However, I left the block on clients without Host headers. When a client doesn't send Host headers, it causes every website hosted at the same IP address/port combination to return the same content. This is probably worse that the invalid SNI host name issue and such clients need to be updated or dropped from use. Though I feel that I made the right decision in allowing SNI-unaware clients to retrieve websites from my server, what initially got me thinking about doing so was the fact that I know a certain someone that prefers not to be mentioned by name used Links to retrieve pages. Links sends Host headers as it should, but doesn't send SNI host names, likely because it doesn't discriminate against certificates that other Web browsers do. If Links suddenly stopped working on my website, it might be seen as some sort of attack on him/her, but that was not at all my goal.

Ronsor has set up an actual home page now, complete with a few other non-RSS pages. The site makes use of frames, which is a bit cumbersome, but it's much better than the single link to a dead site that was there before, is available at / unlike his RSS feed, and is easy to navigate.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Someone wanted to buy //y.st.!

Day 00355: Thursday, 2016 February 25

I spent most of the day cleaning up around the house, but I did get several other things done as well.

I checked on the spider again today and it will take over six months to crawl just the pages of the site that is working on that it has already found. As it finds more pages, that time frame can only go up. It is quite obvious that its current crawling style is not efficient enough and I have shut it down until I can fix it. It should mostly find pages using the method it currently employs, but with the exception that any site that has not been crawled before should have its index page downloaded to fill in the title in the database and to even check to see if the site is running and accessible. Before I can set that up, I need to get scheme-specific normalization set up and figure out how to connect to IRC servers to insure that they are up. I've been rather behind lately though, so it will be a while before I can work on this. In the mean time, there is no point in having the spider continue its crawling. I'm moving before the next time that it saves anything to the database and will have to shut down the spider anyway at that point.

Someone sent me an email using the email address from my whois records. They wanted to buy my domain off me! No specific price offers were made, but he asked if I was willing to part with the name and asked what price I wanted for it. I explained that I couldn't part with the name, but that if he was looking for a short name, he might be able to save himself some effort if he took a look at my notes from when I was looking for a short domain. He said that he had done something similar, but that my notes are more extensive, then asked if he could combine our notes and host them on Github! I told him that my notes are covered by the GNU GPLv3+ and that he could do whatever he liked with them. He never responded to that. Perhaps the free copyleft software license scared him off, as I noticed that the software and services on his own site are proprietary. He also showed me an article about finding short name that is meant to be more interesting and less comprehensive. It seems to fail to recognize that periods are characters when measuring domain name length, but is otherwise an interesting read and is somewhat nostalgic, reminding me of what I saw while looking for my own name.

Him attempting to purchase my domain prompted me to take a look at the available names at the //st. registry again. As I had guessed, all single-character labels have now been registered! Ant to think, I had been crazy enough to consider putting off registration of this domain. I thought that it might be funny to register it on February 29, seeing as that day only comes once every four years. It's arbitrary to be sure, but it would have amused me. I decided not to wait though on the grounds that I had just lost my website including my weblog when my hard drive had died. The sooner I could register the domain, the sooner I could set up a new weblog and get back to having an outlet for my thoughts. While that dead hard drive cost me over a month worth of weblog entries that I was going to migrate to my new short-domain site, it may have saved me from missing out on getting a short name at all. I've learned my lesson too. Don't wait, good names will be snatched up.

I've decided to take one of my onion addresses, probably sbuk7aqcxkoyipwv.onion., and use it to allow access by Tor users to services that typically block Tor users. This will be done with basic onion port forwarding; there won't be any sort of interceptions and transformations by my machine. Web services are off the table, as Host headers will not only give away what is happening, but also will confuse the Web server; it won't know what website it should provide access to. The only Tor-blocking services that I know of right now that this sort of setup will work with are IRC servers. I won't be able to use my onion to connect with these servers myself though, due to the fact that they expose my IP address by design. Other people can hide who they are by using my IP address, but for me to use it, I would need to use someone else's IP address. I can't guarantee that my service will remain unblocked for very long, though perhaps it will help a few people for a while before it gets inevitably blocked. I might reserve some of the ports for internal use, such as port 80 to provide access to a Web page explaining how to get in touch with me and get a service added to my onion. I'll probably look through all the registered schemes, reserve any default ports used by them, then assign the other ports in order starting from one (Tor cannot forward port zero) on a first-come first-serve basis. I discussed the idea with Ronsor for a bit, and I don't think that there will be any issues. Potentially, my IP address will be banned, but that seems a small price to pay when I'm not an exit node yet and I don't otherwise use my home IP address to connect to places.

16:07 <Yst> I've been thinking about it on and off for months. I think that I'm going to set up an onion address that redirects requests to servers that maliciously discriminate against Tor users. Tor users will be able to use my IP address to connect to these services.
16:08 <Yst> I'll probably set up a request form on a Web page.
16:08 <Yst> Then another page with currently-available redirects.
16:08 <@Ronsor> but wont they browse CP via your connection
16:08 <@Ronsor> or drugs or guns
16:08 <Yst> It's not an open proxy, it can't connect to arbitrary places.
16:08 <@Ronsor> now for the sarcastic part: ``needs more children''
16:08 <@Ronsor> oh
16:08 <@Ronsor> so it just redirects a few sites
16:08 <@Ronsor> e.g. google
16:08 <Yst> It only forwards to specific services.
16:08 <Yst> It's port-based.
16:09 <Yst> So <onion>:994 might be freenode, while <onion>:443 might be Google.
16:10 <@Ronsor> oh
16:10 <@Ronsor> nice
16:10 <@Ronsor> cuz google isn't tor-friendly
16:10 <Yst> No, not at all.
16:10 <@Ronsor> i tried using it over tor
16:10 <@Ronsor> i got horrible old unreadable captchas
16:10 <@Ronsor> to do anything
16:11 <Yst> Yeah. Sometimes they don't even have the CAPTCHAs though, they just outright block you.
16:11 <@Ronsor> ikr
16:11 <@Ronsor> i tried as a test to signup for a 'Google-over-Tor' Account
16:12 <@Ronsor> couldn't get past captcha
16:12 <Yst> I'm not sure if a redirect to Google will actually work though, that was just an example. HTTP requests contain Host headers, so Google's servers would be getting hit with requests for the onion address and not know what site to serve.
16:13 <@Ronsor> yeah
16:13 <@Ronsor> and you can't mitm
16:13 <@Ronsor> that's suspicious
16:14 <Yst> I won't man in the middle, even ethics aside. It's outside the scope of what I want to do. I don't want my server even seeing the unencrypted messages.
16:14 <@Ronsor> yeah
16:14 <@Ronsor> maybe you could send people a HOSTS file
16:15 <@Ronsor> and a script to setup proxen for ips: e.g. 127.56.1.2:443 -> google.com
16:15 <@Ronsor> and ncat for a proxy
16:15 <Yst> Huh. That's a thought. I might have to look into setting something up like that.
16:16 <Yst> Ronsor: Do you mind if I quote this conversation?
16:16 <@Ronsor> Yst: i don't mind

When I set up the flash proxy badge at the top of my clearnet website, I had to modify the code a bit to get it to pass validation. Specifically, the <iframe/> tag is deprecated in XHTML 1.1, so I had to replace it with an <object/>code> tag. However, now that my site is using XHTML5, I can once again use <iframe/>s, so I copied the code givn for the flash proxy bade on its instruction page. I ran into a couple issues though. First, a couple of the attributes are still deprecated, so those needed to be removed. Even stranger though, I found that nothing is allowed to go between the <iframe> and </iframe> tags. No elements, no plain text, nothing. So why is there a start and end tag? That's just idiotic. Because I use XHTML, I was able to fix this by making it into one self-closing tag. However, if I were using HTML, this would not be an option and I would been to use this pointless end tag.

Someone that prefers not to be mentioned by name would prefer that I run my IRC server in a more anarchic way, allowing anything that happens to happen. Last time I did this, he and I shared a network, and legal threats were made. One of the channels had sort of become a tiny haven for people of a particular illegal persuasion. It was of no fault of my own and was not something that I ever engaged in. I was the one running the clearnet end of things though, so I was the one open to the possibility of these legal threats. To top it off, he was a bit of a hothead at the time, and had been actively provoking trolls from the safety of onion space. The legal threats were made partially in retaliation. While the trolls were to blame, my partner at the time had been taking unnecessary risks in provoking them. In any case, I had to cut my partnership with him in self defense. His network lives on in onion space, but to avoid such issues on my network, I put rules in place forbidding illegal activity. This person that prefers not to be mentioned by name pulled up a Wikipedia article on Section 230 of the Communications Decency Act, which in theory, should absolve me of liability as long as I don't participate in the illegal activities. I'm going to keep it kind of on the down low, but with this new information in hand, I won't really enforce the network's policy against illegal discussions, at least not using technical means. I don't want to be overly restrictive. At the same time though, I am not going to remove the policy. My server is trapped in onion space by my ISP's restrictive policies; I'm not in onion space to hide. I want a mostly-legal place to discuss, I don't want to run an illegal underground chat platform. I may go into channels and remind people of network policy, but until actual legal action is taken, I won't ban anyone from the network or forcibly disband channels. To discuss the matter of my unofficial policy to refrain from using technical measures to enforce our official network policy, should the need arise, I've set up the channel &Section230, a channel that only exists on one server, even if other servers are added. I'm not sure that ChanServ will be able to protect this channel once services are up though, as ChanServ acts from what is implemented as a second server.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.1 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Add Ted Cruz and Marco Rubio to the list of unfit presidential candidates

Day 00356: Friday, 2016 February 26

Again, I spent most of my time today cleaning up around the house in preparation for my mother's guest. I did take some time out to get some of my own stuff done though.

I compiled the latest stable version of Atheme IRC Services, configured it, and got it set up on my server. I'll probably need to tweak the configuration a bit more later. I definitely need to figure out how to make NickServ automatically identify users by their client TLS certificate.

It seems that Ted Cruz and Marco Rubio, who are currently campaigning to become the next president of my country, are fighting against net neutrality now. I found a nice article on the topic, but at the time of writing, while I am trying to check my sources, the website is hating on Tor users pretty badly. I fill out a CAPTCHA, then get redirected to the home page. No matter how many CAPTCHAs I fill out, every time I try again to load the article, I get hit with another CAPTCHA wall and another redirect to the home page. Clearly, they don't want readers, so I won't send any their way. In any case, this means that Ted Cruz and Marco Rubio need to be added to the list of people that we need to keep out of office.

On #Volatile, z helped me get the Tamsyn font working today. Somehow, it worked without issue this time. Maybe last time I was entering the wrong commands into the command line? I'm not sure. These things would be a lot easier though it there was a way to do them using the graphical interface. There's no reason why a regular user is going to know how to do this on the command line, but that doesn't mean that regular users aren't going to find fonts that they like and that they want to install. It was nice getting to try this font, but now that it's working, I'm not sure how long that I'll actually use it. It's a very limited font and is missing support for non-ASCII characters. It doesn't match the fallback font either, so Unicode characters look out of place when present.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

The Unknown Man surfaces, then disappears again

Day 00357: Saturday, 2016 February 27

We spent the beginning of the day finishing up our cleaning of the house so that my mother's friend could come over. She came and stayed the night, the event that she came to participate in will be tomorrow.

Ronsor added a feedback form on his website, asking for users to rate the site. Strangely enough, any input added to the form will then be sent to your mail client upon submission, then you send the email for it to reach Ronsor. I've never heard of a setup like that. He asked wowaname and I to try it out, so I disabled JavaScript in Iceweasel to try out the site, as I thought that the site made heavy use of JaveScript for some reason and wanted to be sure to test for accesibility. If I was going to give a rating, I was going to actually put in the effort to provide feedback that would actually lead to fixes. However, the site seemd to work pervectly. I didn't test out the chat page, and that probably does require avaScript, but the main pages of the site should and did function. Next, worrying about the heavy use of frames, I tried the website in the Links text-based Web browser. Surprisingly, I found that Links actually handles frames in a reasonable way! I suspect that frames still don't work in some other text-based browsers, but if Links can handle it, maybe that's something that other text-based Web browsers need to fix. With my two major accessibility concerns alleviated, I commented about the fact that the page doesn't pass W3C validation and that HTTPS support would be much appreciated, even if using only a self-signed certificate. I never did go back and check to see if the page validates, as I only care on my own pages when not actively submitting reviews, but Ronsor did set up HTTPS access to his website!

Ronsor did mention that HTTPS support was only set up on his main site though, not the mirrors. The mention of mirrors intrigued me, so I asked about them. For them to be relevant, they needed to be at the same domain as the main site, using some sort of round robin system or the like. If that was the case, I couldn't link to the HTTPS site, as it wouldn't always work depending on which server was queried, but I wouldn't call having several servers on using the same DNS address "mirrors". The alternative would be that there actually were mirrors, but in that case, why even mention them? He obviously cannot control whether mirrors use HTTPS or not, plus there is not mention of mirror addresses on his site. As it turns out, he did indeed actually mean mirrors, and has asked people to mirror his website. He says he'll add instructions for mirroring to the site, so I'll check back later and maybe set up a mirror here in onion space.

On #Volatile, The_Black_V1PER was trying to figure out how to retrieve weather forecasts from wttr.in, which seems to be a pretty cool weather service. In-browser, it sends text colored via <span/> tags, but when used via the command line (for example, using Wget), it colors text using terminal-compatible color byte sequences. I'm not sure exactly how it tells the difference between clients. I suspect that it uses the User-Agent string sent by the client, but if that's the case, it defaults to the HTML version; it sends the HTML version to my Web browser, but my Web browser is set not to send that header. Source code is available for anyone that wants to run their own instance of the service or study how it works.

I managed to get in touch with The Unknown Man today. With my IRC server up and operational, he decided not to invest in an IRS server hosting service, which I think is for the best. We don't have enough users to require multiple servers yet, so it would be wasted money. Hopefully by the time we need more servers, some users will want to add their own machines to the network instead of renting hardware. He also gave me a new email address to reach him at, but my email client is being a pain. It doesn't have an option to manually choose which key to use for encryption and his PGP key specifies his old email address. The email address attached to the key is of course no longer valid too. I need to figure out what to do about this once I have caught up on everything again.

My check from the IRS came today, but I got distracted and didn't get a chance to open the envelope. More importantly, my insurance card came. Oddly enough, twelve insurgence cards came, but two were blank and nine were voided out. It seems like a waste of paper, but whatever. I still find it idiotic that health insurance has become mandatory, but at least i have that out of the way for this year.

I added client certificate recognition to NickServ. It only involved uncommenting a single line. I'm not sure why this is disabled by default, to be honest. In any case, if you configure your NickServ account with your client certificate fingerprint, you will now be identified by NickServ automatically.

I was discussing SD cards with someone on Tox today, and came across some interesting information. I had thought it stupid that mobile devices can only handle SD cards up to a certain size. After all, an SD card is an SD card, right? However, I didn't really question it. However, if the person I was speaking to is correct, the information about maximum SD card size is actually a lie. A regular SD card can only be built to carry so much, but a different standard, SDXC, can be used to create cards that hold even more. He said that a device that can handle one size of SDXC card can handle an SDXC card of any size. The SDXC standard covers SD cards with sizes ranging from 64 gigabytes to 2 terabytes, so because my device can supposedly handle cards up to 64 gigabytes in size, it should also be able to handle larger cards up to 2 terabytes in size. This is awesome! I don't need a card quite that big yet, but when I get there, I won't need to trim my music collection, I'll just need to get a bigger card. By that time, SD card prices will probably have fallen even lower too.

I read an interesting article on the illusion of decentralization. Basically, the point the article makes is that you cannot decentralize everything; it simple isn't possible without making communication impossible. When communication is centralized, these central authorities are able to create whatever "standard" that is used for their platforms. You end up with many different services, each with their own protocol. The development of such communication protocols is decentralized. However, in order to create a platform in which communication is decentralized, all participants must agree on a standard. There could be thousands of servers deployed by varying individuals and companies, but development of the protocols must be centralized. Without centrally-developed protocols, the many nodes are not speaking the same language and are unable to properly interact. The article argued that this later strategy, what we normally think of as "decentralized", is actually even more centralized than "centralized" services. What these "decentralized" services actually offer isn't decentralization, but a consistent and stable set of rules. We need to stop focusing on "decentralization", and instead ask ourselves and each other what set of rules actually work best for us as users. Personally, being able to keep our own data in our own hands seems to be a pretty good reason for sticking with standardized protocols, but we need to make sure that these protocols are well-designed enough to actually provide us with what we need.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Ronsor Public License v2.5

Day 00359: Monday, 2016 February 29

Today is the day I was planning to buy a short domain originally. Thankfully, I made the purchase back when a short name was actually available. There are no more short names that are available in DNS spaces that are not run by registries that ask for telephone numbers from their customers. I thought that it would be fun to have a short domain purchased on a date that only occurs once every four years, but that's a stupid arbitrary reason to wait to register a domain. If I had waited, I would not have a short domain at all, or if I did, it wouldn't be in what i later discovered was my favorite name space.

Mother's friend went home this morning.

I've been meaning to submit feedback for the local community college's online orientation, but I hadn't gotten around to it yet. Today, I emailed that in, on the final day that feedback would be accepted. I really wish I wasn't so far behind. It would have helped if I didn't spend yesterday taking a break.

Ronsor found out that his <form/> that submits to an email address is actually nonstandard, but works in many Web browsers. I didn't look into the standard myself, but it is kind of odd that it works. He also said that he's releasing his website under the Ronsor Public License v2.5, which is just the short text Do whatever you want except take credit for it. I'd like you to notify me if you redistribute my content, but it is not mandatory.. It is now free, so when I finally catch up on everything that I need to get done, I will probably set up a mirror. I get the feeling that a certain someone pressured him into releasing it freely; it wasn't me. He also has his own search engine. It is possible to submit URIs for inclusion, but this is done via email. I can't help but think that this means that he has to add URIs manually. I try not to beg people to link to me, so I didn't send in my URI for inclusion.

Ronsor also tried to get me to start using cjdns. After looking into how it works, I was less than enthusiastic. Unlike Tor, there is no central authority; you can't just join the network. In fact, there is no one network. Instead, there are several independent networks, and to join any of them, you need to obtain permission from someone already on that network, at which point you connect your node to theirs. This introduces a number of issues. First of all, this is a trust-based networking model. I strongly feel that trust in any individual is a weak link. It either kills anonymity or involves taking the blame for people that you "trusted", but didn't actually know. Second, when connecting to the network directly through their node, what happens if their node goes down? My assumption is that you lose access to the network until their node goes back up. There's no redundancy. Obviously, I cannot use this for anything serious, but Ronsor is my friend, so I expressed my concerns but tried to set it up anyway. I figured I could connect through cjdns to Ronsor's server like he wanted, but not use it for anything else. There is no package for cjdns in the Debian repositories, so I tried to compile it from source. I never could get it to successfully compile though. I just kept running into an error about the Node.js archive that the compilation script tried to download being corrupted:

==> Downloading http://nodejs.org/dist/v0.10.24/node-v0.10.24-linux-x64.tar.gz with wget...
	DONE!
==> Verifying the checksum of the downloaded archive...
	ERROR: The downloaded file is damaged! Aborting

My system's package of Node.js was too old, so the compilation script couldn't use it, and I tried downloading the archive myself and putting it in the source directory, but the compilation script didn't check for it there. I strongly suspect that it's failing to download the archive, not that the archive is actually damaged, but in either case, I'm not sure why it's happening. There doesn't seem to be a reason that the download would fail or would come through damaged. I ended up giving up on this task for the day.

I ended up at a restaurant today, so I ordered the only seemingly-vegan item on the menu. However, I've learned from past experience at this restaurant that while the ingredients that they admit on the menu are included are vegan, the chefs add sour cream and cheese to the actual burrito. Yuck! So, I specifically asked that the sour cream and cheese be left off. However, they spaced it and added them anyway. I really feel bad having to have sent it back. It seems like such a waste of food. However, milk products literally give me a headache. It's not fair that I should get a headache just because they a) include extra ingredients that they don't mention on the menu and b) failed to leave them off when I asked that they be left off.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.